<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>תלמוד ירושלמי מסכת שבת פרק יב דף יג עמוד ב /מ"גSERG2020-07-12unknownConverted from a Word documentDOCX to TEI2020-07-15T21:53:18ZSERGאלישבע Biblical, Exod 6:23. אלישבע was Aaron’s wife. – Elisheba O: – Ds: Nehemiah (12) and Jonathan (31)’s mother F: Amulet, Nazareth? The owner of the amulet reports that he found it in a field near Nazereth. S: Hamilton, JSS 41 (1996) 221 E: – D: 6th Cאסתר Biblical, e.g. Esth 2:7. אסתר was the queen who gave her name to the biblical book.  – EstherO: ̓Εσθ[ήρ] Reading reconstructed by editor, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.1, p. 11. Although this form is not recorded elsewhere, this is obviously the name intended. Ds: Samuel (35) and Tanḥum (28)’s mother F: Inscription, Admedera, North-east of Damascus. Vidua S: CIJ 848 E: –  The suggestion that this is a Jewish inscription is based, 1. On the formula Εἱς Θεός (God is one), but see Introduction 6.1.6; 2. The biblical name Samuel (35) is found in the inscription, but he could be Christian, see vol. 3, Introduction 6.6.7, p. 52; 3. However, the name of her son, Tanḥum, was clearly Jewish, see Introduction 6.2.2.4.D: 5th CO: ̓Αρτήρ For this form see vol. 3, under Aster G/F, p. 407. Ds: Salome (2)’s mother F: Amulet, Beirut, Seyrig S: CIJ 874 E: – The inscription is accompanied by the Hebrew word שלום (peace), see vol. 3, Introduction 6.2, pp. 33-4. D: 5th-7th C I have inserted these dates when editors claimed the composition or find was Byzantine, see Introduction 7.5.5.O: ̓Αστερίου For this form see vol. 3, under Asteria G/F, p. 407.  Ds: – F: Epitaph, Jaffa, Schick S: CIJ 910 E: – D: 3rd CO: ̓Αστερίου See previous note. Ds: Zachariah (9)’s mother F: Epitaph, Jaffa, Vincent S: CIJ 916 E: Female? The decision to list this person as female is based on the fact that the name was more common for females, but the male ̓Αστερίος is also recorded. D: 3rd CO: ̓Ισθήρ The epitaphs are bilingual – Hebrew and Greek. The Hebrew (BS 1:126) has אסתר. So in the Greek (BS 2:88). Although this form is not recorded elsewhere, this is obviously the name intended. Ds: Amphithea (1) F: Epitaphs, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 3, CIJ 1009 S: 1. BS 1:126; 2. 2:88 E: – D: Pre-352 This is the year in which Beth She‘arim was destroyed, see Introduction 7.5.1. O: Εἰσθήρ Although this form is not recorded elsewhere, this is obviously the name intended. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 1, CIJ 1050 S: BS 2:39 E: – D: Pre-352 See above, n. 12. O: ̓Ασθήρ For this form see vol. 3, under Esther (3) B/F, p. 175. Ds: Anthus (1)’s daughter, of Tyre In Greek – Τυρία (in Lebanon). On such designations see vol. 1, Introduction 3.2.6, p. 34. F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 12, S: BS 2:147 E: – D: Pre-352 See above, n. 12. O: ̓Αστήρ For this form see vol. 3, under Aster G/F, p. 407. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 15 S: BS 2:176 E: – D: Pre-352 This is the year in which Beth She‘arim was destroyed, see Introduction 7.5.1. O: – Ds: Adio (1)’s daughter F: Epitaph, Zoar S: Ben-Zvi, BIES 10 (1943) 37 (no. 2) E: – D: 450 The inscription is dated to 380 years after the destruction, see Introduction 7.5.2.1.O: ̓Αστή Though not recorded elsewhere, I assume this is the name intended. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Caesarea S: Lehmann &amp; Holum CMER 5, no. 165 E: Proselyte In Greek – προσσυλήτου. D: 3rd-4thO: ̓Ασθή[ρι] Reading reconstructed by editor, see above, n. 15. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Caesarea S: Lehmann &amp; Holum, CMER 5, no. 270 E: Jew? Jewishness may be suggested based on name, but see vol. 3, Introduction 6.6.7, p. 52. The city of Caesarea included a mixed population of Jews pagans and Christians, see Introduction 6.2.1.2. D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60.O: – Ds: Bebai (10)’s daughter F: Epitaph, Zoar S: Naveh, Tarbiz 64 (1995) no. 11 E: – D: 468 The inscription is dated to 398 years after the destruction of the Temple, see Introduction 7.5.2.1. O: אסתיר On the additional י as a dialect variant see vol 4, Introduction 2.3.5.2, p. 13. This may be a transliteration of the name back from the Greek into Jewish characters, see Introduction 2.2. Ds: Eleazar (61)’s mother F: Amulet, Horvat Kanaf In the Golan, north east of the Sea of Galilee.  S: AMB no. 3 E: – D: 350-500O: – Ds: Tate (2)’s daughter F: Amulet, Nirim In the north-western Negev. S: AMB no. 13 E: – D: 5th Cדבורה Biblical, e.g. Judg 4:4. דבורה was an important prophetess and judge.  − DeborahO: Δεβωρᾶς In LXX the name is transliterated Δεββ́ρα (H &amp; R Suppl. 51). In Josephus Δαβ́ρα. This is somewhere in the middle, see vol. 1, Introduction 2.1.1 and 2.1.1.1, pp. 17-8. Ds: Samuel (38)’s daughter, aged 4 In Greek – δ.́ On these details see vol. 3, Introduction 3.1, p. 21. F: Epitaph, Beirut, Renan S: CIJ 873 E: − The inscription is accompanied by a menorah, see vol. 3, Introduction 6.3.1, p. 35. D: 6th Cדינה Biblical, e.g. Gen 30:21. דינה was Jacob’s daughter. − DinahO: Δινά One of the forms in which this name was transliterated into Greek in translations of the Bible, see H &amp; R Suppl. 51.  Ds: – F: Epitaph, Tabgha Located on the northern shore of the Sea of Galilee., Schneider S: Klein, Yeshuv, 39 E: – D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60.הגר Biblical, e.g. Gen 16:1. הגר was Abraham’s concubine. − Hagar O: ̓Αγαρεα In LXX the transliteration of this name is ̔Αγάρ. Josephus has ̔Αγάρη, see vol. 1, Introduction 2.1.1 and 2.1.1.1, pp. 17-8. However the suffix here looks like it is a transformation of a Latin genitive case ending, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.4.2.2.1, p. 18. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Ashdot Ya‘aqov Kibbutz south of the Sea of Galilee. S: Ovadiah, Atiqot 5 (1969 – HS) 84 E: Jew? Jewishness may be suggested based on name, but see vol. 3, Introduction 6.6.7, p. 52. Also, on how exact the name is see above, n. 2. D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60.חנה Biblical, e.g. 1 Sam 1:2. חנה was the prophet Samuel’s mother. − Hannah O: ܐܢܐ So in Syriac, ROC1/9 (1904) 88, see vol. 4, Introduction 2.8.1, pp. 18-9. In Hebrew this would read אנא. Te name seems like a transliteration back into Semiic chatacters from the Greek form of the name see Introduction 2.2. /ⲁⲛⲛⲁ So in Coptic, ROC1/9 (1904) 320, see vol. 1, Introduction 2.8.4, p. 31. In Greek this would read ̓́Αννα. For this form see vol. 3, under Hannah (1) B/F, p. 177. Ds: Judah (3) Quiriacus (1)’s mother F: – S: Guidi, ROC1/9 (1904) 88, 320 E: Christian convert The text describes her son’s conversion, elevation to the bishophood and subsequent martyrdom at the hands of Julian the apostate. She is also described as accepting his faith.; fictitious This is a famous legend. D: 326-8 These are the years of Helena’s visit to Jerusalem, see Introduction 7.1.O: – Ds: Abba (3)’s mother On sages in this family being called after their mothers see Ilan, Silencing the Queen, 254-5. F: – S: yBer 1:1, 3a (Kosovsky, Yerushalmi, 11-12) E: – D: 3rd C Her son was a contemporary of Rabbi Yohanan (1), see Introduction 7.4.1.O: – Ds: Isaac (11)’s wife F: – S: bTaan 23b Although told in BT, the aim of this story is demonstrate the behaviour of the “great ones” of the Land of Israel (תקיפי דארעא דישראל), see Introduction 5.1.3.2.1. (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 501) E: − Although mentioned only in BT, she is the wife of a Palestinian rabbi. D: 4th C Her husband is a contemporary of Rabbi Yonah (2)’s son, see Introduction 7.4.3.O: ̓́Αννα See above, n. 3. Ds: Hilasius (3)’s daughter F: Epitaph, Jaffa, Clermont-Ganneau S: CIJ 907 E: – D: 3rd CO: ̓Ανα My reading. The editor read ̓Ανα[νία]. For this form see vol. 3, under Hannah (3) B/F, p. 177. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Jaffa, Clermont-Ganneau S: CIJ 921 E: – D: 3rd CO: ̓́Αννα See above, n. 3. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 1, CIJ 1013, 1014 S: 1. BS 2:2; 2. 2:3 E: – D: Pre-352 This is the year in which Beth She‘arim was destroyed, see Introduction 7.5.1. O: ̓́Αννα See above, n. 3. Ds: Mistress In Greek, in Jewish characters – קירא. On this title see Introduction 3.1.3.2. F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 1, CIJ 1088 S: BS 2:70 E: – D: Pre-352 See above, n. 15. O: ̓́Αννα For this form see vol. 1, under Hannah (1) B/F, p. 240. Ds: Peitholaus (2)’s daughter, aged 55 In Greek – ἐτῶν πεντήκοντα. On these details see vol. 3, Introduction 3.1, p. 21. F: Epitaph, Zoar S: IPT 1b, no. 10 E: Jew? The inscription is neither specifically Christian, nor undoubtedly pagan. Since the Zoar cemetery includes Jewish tombstones, this one could also be Jewish, see Introduction 6.2.1.1. D: 390 The inscription is dated, according to the era of the Province of Arabia, see Introduction 7.5.2.2.O:  Αννας For this form see vol. 3, under Hannah (6) B/F, p. 177. Ds: Mattathias (5)’s daughter, of Beit She‘arim In Greek – Βισαρηνή. F: Epitaph, Ben Shemen East of Tel Aviv. S: Avi-Yonah, BIES 9 (1942) 31 E: – Jewishness suggested based on both names. Usually this would not be enough, but her father’s name, Μαθιθία in this form, rather than Mathias, would be typically Jewish (Introduction 6.2.2) and the provenance of these people (Beit She‘arim) also suggests Jewishness, see Introduction 5.2.2.2). D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60.O: – Ds: Haniel (2)’s daughter F: Epitaph, Zoar S: Misgav IMSA 5 (2006) no. 31 E: – D: 439 The inscription is dated to 369 years after the destruction of the Temple, see Introduction 7.5.2.1.יוחנה יוחנה is the feminine form of the biblical יוחנן. It is, however, never mentioned in the Bible. For female names derived from male names see vol. 3, Introduction 1.1.2.1, p. 6.  − Joanna O: יוחני For this form see vol. 1, under Joanna (6) S-H/F, p. 420. Ds: Retavi (1)’s daughter F: – S: bSot 22a Although mentioned only in BT, she is associated in this tradition with Rabbi Yohanan (1), and see Introduction 5.1.3.2.3. (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 702) E: – D: 3rd C  She is mentioned in a tradition cited by Rabbi Yohanan (1), see Introduction 7.4.1.O: – Ds: Qoqah (1)’s daughter F: Epitaph, Zoar S: Naveh, Tarbiz 69 (2000) no. 19 E: – D: 356 The inscription is dated to 286 years after the destruction of the Temple, see Introduction 7.5.2.1.O: ̓Ιωανα For this form see vol. 1, under Joanna (7) S-H/F, p. 420. Ds: Marciana (2), craftswoman In Greek – τεχνίτη. On such designations see Introduction 3.1.3.3. F: Dedicatory inscription, Syria S: Jarry, Annales Islamologique 9 (1970) no. 31 E: Jew? The inscription contains the formula Εἵς θεός (one God), but bears no Christian markers, see Introduction 6.1.6. Male? Jarry translates ̓Ιωανα Μαρκιανη τεχνίτη ἐπηησαν  with “Jean et Marcien mâitres d’oeuvre ont fait.” According to him the orthographie is “extrêmement fantaisiste,” interpreting the names as those of two males. However, this is unlikely. D: 540/1 The inscription is dated according to the Seleucid era, see Introduction 7.5.4.1.לאה Biblical, e.g. Gen 29:16. לאה was Jacob’s first wife.  − Leah O: Λήα The form of this name in LXX is Λεία, see H &amp; R Suppl 101. On the interchange of ει and η see vol. 1, Introduction 2.3.2, p. 21. Ds: Benjamin (12)’s daughter F: Epitaph, Caesarea, Sukenik S: CIJ 888 E: Jew? Jewishness may be suggested based on name, but see vol. 3, Introduction 6.6.7, p. 52. The region was not particularly Jewish, see Introduction 6.2.1.2. D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60. מיכאלה מיכאלה is the feminine form of the biblical מיכאל (e.g. Num 13:13). It is, however, never mentioned in the Bible, and thus not counted as biblical. For female names derived from male names see vol. 3, Introduction 1.1.2.1, p. 6.  – MikelaO: Μικέλα The epitaph is bilingual. So in the Greek. We may be certain this is the name intended here because of the Hebrew parallel./מיכאלא The epitaph is bilingual. So in the Hebrew. On the replacement of the ה suffix with א see vol. 1, Introduction 2.4.2.7, p. 26. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 8, CIJ 1155 S: BS 2:122 E: – D: Pre-352 This is the year in which Beth She‘arim was destroyed, see Introduction 7.5.1. מלכה Biblical, e.g. Num 26:33.− Malka O: Μελχά This is how this name is spelt in LXX, see H &amp; R Suppl. 111. Ds: Sarah (3)’s daughter, aged 13 In Greek – ἔτ(η) ιγ.́ On these see details vol. 3, Introduction 3.1, p. 21. F: Sarcophagus, Sichem-Nablus, Berger S: CIJ 1169 E: Samaritan? The location of the find suggests this, but see Introduction 6.1.5. D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60. מרים Biblical, e.g. Exod 15:20. מרים was Moses’ sister.  − MariamO: – In the Samaritan script, see Introduction 2.5.1. Ds: Eleazar (3)’s daughter F: – S: 1. Tulida, 142; 2. Abu’l Fath, 177 E: Samaritan These are Samaritan chronicle, see Introduction 5.1.2.1. All the persons mentioned in them, unless otherwise stated, are Samaritans, see Introduction 6.1.2. D: 4th C Chronology calculated roughly according to the Tulida, see Introduction 7.2.1.O: – See above, n. 2..  Ds: Aqub (2)’s daughter F: – S: Abu’l Fath, 161 E: Samaritan See above, n. 3. D: 3rd C See above, n. 4.O: Μαρίας On this form see vol. 3, under Mariam (12) B/F, p. 180. Ds: Anatolius (2)’s daughter F: Epitaph, Jaffa, Clermont-Ganneau S: CIJ 937 E: – D: 3rd CO: Μαρίας See previous note. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Caesarea, Germer-Durand S: CIJ 938 E: Jew? Jewishness may be suggested based on names found on the inscription, but see vol. 3, Introduction 6.6.7, p. 52. The region was not particularly Jewish, see Introduction 6.2.1.2. D: 3rd CO: מירים So in BS 1:8 in Hebrew. On the additional י as a dialect variant see vol 4, Introduction 2.3.5.2, p. 13./Μαριάμ[μη] So in BS 2:9 in Greek. Reading reconstructed by editor, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.1, p. 11. On this form see vol. 1, under Mariam (1) B/F, p. 242. On the double consonant μ see vol. 1, Introduction 2.3.4, p. 22. Ds: – F: Epitaphs, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 1, CIJ 1019, 1020, 1021 S: 1. BS 1:8, 2. 2:9 E: – D: Pre-352 This is the year in which Beth She‘arim was destroyed, see Introduction 7.5.1. O: Μαριαμ For this form see vol. 1, under Mariam (11) B/F, p. 242. Ds: Judah (86)’s daughter, mistress In Greek – κυρά. On this title see Introduction 3.1.3.2. F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 25 S: BS 2:219 E: – D: Pre-352 See above, n. 13. O: – Ds: Yohanan (28)’s daughter F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 20 S: BS 3:21 E: – D: Pre-352 See above, n. 13. O: Μαρίας See above, n. 8. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Caesarea S: Lehmann &amp; Holum, CMER 5, no. 301 E: Jew? See above, n. 10. D: 4th-7th CO: [Μ]αρία[ς] Reading reconstructed by editor, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.1, p. 11. On this form see above, n. 8. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Caesarea S: Lehmann &amp; Holum, CMER 5, no. 302 E: Jew? See above, n. 10. D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60.O: Μαρ[ίας] Reading reconstructed by editor, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.1, p. 11. On this form see above, n. 8. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Caesarea S: Lehmann &amp; Holum, CMER 5, no. 303 E: Jew? See above, n. 10. D: – See above, n. 22.O: – Ds: – F: Epitaph, Zoar S: Naveh, Tarbiz 64 (1995) no. 8 E: – D: 382-452 The inscription is dated to the destruction of the Temple, but is unclear at this point. According to the 7 year cycle that is also documented on the inscription, this could be either 312 or 382, see Introduction 7.5.2.1.O: Μαρία[ς] Reading reconstructed by editor, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.1, p. 11. On this form see above, n. 8. Ds: Elijah (6)’s wife, of Bostra In Greek – Βοσστρ[ην]ῆς. On Bostra see Introduction 3.2.1. F: Memorial inscription, Hammat Gader S: Di Segni, Hammat Gader, no. 38 E: Jew? Jewishness suggested by Di Segni, based on name, but see vol. 3, Introduction 6.6.7, p. 52.  D: 5th-6th Cצפרה Biblical, e.g. Exod 2:22. Sipora was Moses’ wife.  − SiporaO: ציפור The י here has a vowel function, see vol. 4, Introduction 2.3.5.2, p. 13. The fall of the ה is inexplicable.. Ds: Abshalom (1)’s daughter F: – S: yGit 5:3, 46d (Kosovsky, Yerushalmi, 55) E: – D: 3rd-4th C She is mentioned in association with Eleazar (8), see Introduction 7.4.3.רבקה Biblical, e.g. Gen 22:23. רבקה was Isaac’s wife.  − Rebekah O: – Ds: Levi (5)’s wife F: – S: Cohen, Chronicle, 56 Stenhouse claims that she is also mentioned in Abu’l Fath, 161, but I was not able to read her name in the Arabic. E: Samaritan This is a Samaritan chronicle, see Introduction 5.1.2. All the persons mentioned in it, unless otherwise stated, are Samaritans, see Introduction 6.1.2. D: 3rd-4th C These are the dates of Baba Rabba (Bebai [1]). She is his contemporary, see Introdution 7.2.3.O: ̔Ρεβέκκα For this form see vol. 3, under Rebecca (1) B/F, p. 185. Ds: Mana (8)’s mother, Rufinius (1)’s wife F: Epitaph, Jaffa, Savignac, Euting S: CIJ 948, 949 E: – D: 3rd CO: – Ds: Phineas (17)’s wife F: Synagogue inscription, Na‘aran, North of Jericho. Vincent &amp; Carrière S: CIJ 1198 E: – D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60.O: ̔Ρεβε[κας] Reading reconstructed by the editor, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.1. For this form see vol. 3, under Rebecca (6) B/F, p. 185. Ds: Zosimus (2)’s sister F: Synagogue inscription, Mount Gerizim S: Gerizim II, p. 248. E: Samaritan This is a Samaritan synagogue, see Introduction 6.1.4. D: 4th-5th C  Biblical, e.g. Ruth 1:4. רות is the Moabite woman who gave the book the name.רות− Ruth O: Ρεούθ In LXX her name is recorded as ̔Ρούθ, see H &amp; R Suppl. 131. The additional ε may be a scribal error, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.8.1, p. 20. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 1, CIJ 1061, 1065 S: 1. BS 1:69, 2. 2:48 E: – D: Pre-352 This is the year in which Beth She‘arim was destroyed, see Introduction 7.5.1. רחל Biblical, e.g. Gen 29:6. רחל was Jacob’s beloved wife.  − RachelO: ̔Ραήλ This is an unusual form but the intention is clear. Either the χ has fallen (as in vol. 1, under Rachel (1), B/F, p. 248), as a result of a scribal error, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.8.2, p. 20, or this is a nother dialect, indicating the decline of the laryngeals, see vol. 1, Introduction 2.5.1, p. 28. Ds: Urania (2), of Esia In Greek – ̓Ασιθα. Probably biblical Ezion-Geber, according to the editors. On this sort of designation see vol. 1, Introduction 3.2.6, p. 34. F: Epitaph, catacomb 8, CIJ 1154 S: BS 2:121 E: – D: Pre-352 This is the year in which Beth She‘arim was destroyed, see Introduction 7.5.1. שבתית שבתית is the feminine form of the biblical שבתאי (e.g. Ezra 10:15). It is, however, never mentioned in the Bible. It was probably invented in post-biblical times, see vol. 3, Introduction 1.1.2.1, p. 6.  – ShabtitO: סמבטי On the form סמבטי see vol. 3, Under Shabtai (113) B/M, p. 152. This is the Greek form of this name, transliterated back into Hebrew, see Introduction 2.2. Ds: Archon, aged 40 In Hebrew – [אר]כונית, [אר]בעים שנ[ה]. On this title as the feminine for archon, and its implications see D. Stoekel Ben Ezra, “A Jewish Archontess: Remarks on an Epitaph from Byblos,” ZPE 169 (2009) 287-93. On the age details see vol. 3, Introduction 3.1, p. 21. F: Epitaph, Biblos, In Lebanon. Renan S: CIJ 869 E: – The inscription is in Hebrew characters, see vol. 3, Introduction 6.2, pp. 33-4. D: 385/6 According to IJO 3, Syr30 the inscription is dated to the destruction of the Temple, see Introduction 7.5.4.1.שלום In the Bible שלום is recorded only as a man’s name (one of the last kings of Israel, e.g. 2 Kgs 15:10).  − SalomeO: Σαλαφθᾶ Although it is very remote from the original, I assume this is the name intended. Ds: – F: – S: Prophyry 98 E: Christian convert  She is described in this text as choosing to convert to Christianity (ibid.,100) which suggests that to begin with she was not Christian. With such a name (translated in the text to Greek as Εἰρήνη – peace, ibid., 98) living in Gaza in Palestine, she was initially probably Jewish.D: Pre-407 The calculation was made by the editor of this document. O: Σαλόμῃ For this form see vol. 1, under Salome (1) B/F, p. 249. On the interchange of ω and ο see vol. 1, Introduction 2.3.3.1, p. 22. Ds: Esther (2)’s daughter F: Amulet, Beirut, Seyrig S: CIJ 874 E: – The inscription is accompanied by the Hebrew word שלום (peace), see vol. 3, Introduction 6.2, pp. 33-4. D: 5th-7th C I have inserted these dates when editors claimed the composition or find was Byzantine, see Introduction 7.5.5.O: Σ[αλ]́μην Reading reconstructed by editor, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.1, p. 11. For this form see vol. 1, under Salome (1) B/F, p. 249. Ds: Aged 22, maiden In Greek – [ἔ]τ[η] κβ́ νύμφην. On these details see vol. 3, Introduction 3.1, p. 21. On the description see Introduction 3.1.3.7.2. F: Epitaph, Tiberias, Frey S: CIJ 984 E: – Jewishness indicated by name, see Introduction 6.2.2. D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60.O: שלמת This is an unusual transliteration of this name, but see Σαλαμάθ in vol. 1, under Salome (10), B/F, p. 249. On this feminine suffix see vol. 1, Introduction 2.4.4.1, pp. 27-8. Ds: Rishah (2)’s daughter F: Epitaphs, Beth She‘arim S: 1. CIJ 1144; 2. 1145 E: – D: Pre-352 This is the year in which Beth She‘arim was destroyed, see Introduction 7.5.1. O: – Ds: – F: Epitaph, Sidon, In Lebanon. Contenau S: IJO 3, Syr15 E: – The editor suggested this was a blessing, but see Ilan Silencing the Queen, 261-75. D: – See above, n. 11.O: – Ds: – F: Sarcophagus, Tiberias S: Schwabe, Yohanan Levi, no. 1 E: – The editor thinks this is a blessing, but it could also be the name of the deceased, see Ilan, Silencing the Queen, 261-75. D: 3rd CO: סלמינו I assume this is the Greek form of this name, transliterated back into Hebrew, see Introduction 2.2. Ds: Cosmus (2)’s mother F: Amulet, Hecht Museum, Haifa S: AMB no. 1 E: – D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60.שפרה Biblical, Exod 1:15. שפרה was a Jewish midwife at the time of the Exodus.  − Shiphra O: [Σ]αφίρα Reading reconstructed by editor, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.1, p. 11. For this form see vol. 1, under Shiphra (9), p. 254. Ds: Hananiah (55)’s mother F: Epitaph, Caesarea S: Lehmann &amp; Holum, CMER 5, no. 346 E: Jew? Jewishness may be suggested based on name, but see vol. 3, Introduction 6.6.7, p. 52. The region was not particularly Jewish, see Introduction 6.2.1.2. D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60.O: שפירא For this form see vol. 1, under Shiphra (3) B/F, p. 254. Ds: Simon (81)’s mother F: Amulet, Munich, private collection S: AMB no. 14 E: – D: – See above, n. 4.שרה Biblical, e.g. Gen. 17:15. שרה was Abraham’s wife.  − Sarah O: ﻩﺮﺳ In Arabic, see Introduction 2.5.2. In Hebrew this would read שרה./שושנה So according to Adler &amp; Séligsohn, REJ 45 (1902) 232. For this name see under Susanna S-H/F.  Ds: Mariam (2)’s daughter F: – S: Abu’l Fath, 177 E: Samaritan This is a Samaritan chronicle, see Introduction 5.1.2.2. All the persons mentioned in it, unless otherwise stated, are Samaritans, see Introduction 6.1.2. D: 3rd C Chronology calculated roughly according to the Tulida, see Introduction 7.2.1.O: Σάρα For this form see vol. 1, under Sarah (6) B/F, p. 255. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Jaffa, Sukenik S: CIJ 942 E: – D: 3rd CO: Σάρρα For this form see vol. 1, under Sarah (1) B/F, p. 254. Ds: Chairemon (1)’s daughter, aged 50 In Greek – ἔτ(η) ν́. On these details see vol. 3, Introduction 3.1, p. 21. F: Sarcophagus, Sichem-Nablus, Berger S: CIJ 1169 E: Samaritan? The location of the find suggests this, but see Introduction 6.1.5. D: – The inscription is not dated. Late antique date presumed, see vol. 3, Introduction 8.3, p. 60.O: Σάρρα See above, n. 7. Ds: Sarah (3)’s daughter, virgin aged 14 In Greek – παρθ(ένος) ἔτ(η) ιδ.́ On these details see vol. 3, Introduction 3.1, p. 21. On the designation see Introduction 3.1.3.7.2. F: Sarcophagus, Sichem-Nablus, Berger S: CIJ 1169 E: Samaritan? See above, n. 9. D: – See above, n. 10.O: Σάρα See above, n. 6. Ds: Joseph (87)’s mother F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 1, CIJ 997 S: BS 2:22 E: – D: Pre-352 This is the year in which Beth She‘arim was destroyed, see Introduction 7.5.1. O: [Σ]άρα So in BS 2:85. Reconstructed by the editor. For this form see above, n. 6./Σά[ρ]α So in BS 2:86. See previous note Ds: Quirinius (1)’s daughter F: Epitaphs, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 3, CIJ 1107, 1108 S: 1. BS 2:85; 2. 2:86 E: – D: Pre-352 See above, n. 16. O: Σάρα See above, n. 6. Ds: Judah (76)’s sister, Isaac (47)’s wife F: Epitaphs, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 1, CIJ 1045, 1047 S: 1. BS 2:34; 2. 2:36 E: – D: Pre-352 See above, n. 16. O: Σάρα See above, n. 6. Ds: Nehemiah (9)’s daughter F: Epitaphs, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 1, CIJ 1007, 1085 S: 1. BS 2:66; 2. 2:68 E: – D: Pre-352 See above, n. 16. O: Σάρα See above, n. 6. Ds: The pious In Greek – ̔σία. On such designations see Introduction 3.1.3.7.1. F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 13 S: BS 2:158 E: – D: Pre-352 See above, n. 16. O: Σάρα See above, n. 6. Ds: Joseph (92)’s wife F: Epitaphs, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 13 S: 1. BS 2:160; 2. 2:161 E: – D: Pre-352 See above, n. 16. O: Σάρα See above, n. 6. Ds: Theodosia (1), of Tyre In Greek – Τυρίας. On such designations vol. 1, Introduction 3.2.6, p. 34. F: Epitaph, Beth She‘arim, catacomb 21 S: BS 2:199 E: – D: Pre-352 See above, n. 16. O: Σάρας For this form see vol. 1, under Sarah (5) B/F, p. 255. Ds: Marcellus (1)’s daughter F: Epitaph, Tyre In southern Lebanon. S: Rey-Coquais, Tyr, no. 164 E: Jew?  Jewishness suggested based on name, but see vol. 3, Introduction 6.6.7, p. 52.D: – See above, n. 10.O: Σάρας See above, n. 32. Ds: – F: Epitaph, Caesarea S: Lehmann &amp; Holum CMER 5, no. 263 E: Jew? See above, n. 34. D: – See above, n. 10.O: שארה On the additional א as a dialect variant see vol 4, Introduction 2.3.5.3, p. 13. Ds: Natrun (1)’s mother F: Amulet, Nirim In the north-western Negev. S: AMB no. 11 E: – D: 5th CO: – Ds: Marin (3)’s mother F: Amulet, Irbid In Jordan. S: MSF nos. 27, 28 E: – D: – See above, n. 10.O: סורה For this form see vol. 1, under Sarah (2) B/F, p. 254. On the additional ו as a dialect variant see vol 4, Introduction 2.3.5.1, p. 13. Ds: Sarah (17)’s daughter F: Amulet, Irbid See above, n. 41. S: MSF no. 30 E: – D: – See above, n. 10.O: סרה For this form see vol. 1, under Sarah (2) B/F, p. 254. This may be a transliteration back from the Greek into Jewish characters, see Introduction 2.2. Ds: Sarah (16)’s mother F: Amulet, Irbid See above, n. 41. S: MSF no. 30 E: – D: – See above, n. 10.תמר Biblical, e.g. Gen 38:6. תמר was Judah’s daughter-in-law and mother of his children.  − TamarO: – Ds: – F: – S: yMeg 3:2, 74a (Kosovsky, Yerushalmi, 682) E: – D: 3rd C She is a contemporary of Rabbi Abbahu (1), who is a contemporary of Rabbi Yohanan (1), see Introduction 7.4.1.