<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    
        
            
                Arabic Names (male):
                kerstinhuenefeld
            
            
                2020-08-03
            
            
                unknown
            
            
                Converted from a Word document
            
        
        
            
                
                    DOCX to TEI
                
            
        
        
            
                2020-08-03T05:37:00Zkerstinhuenefeld
            
        
    
    
        
            
                
                    Arabic Names – Male 
                    ابشعر Arabic
                                (ʾBŠʿR), see Harding, ICPIANI, 12.
                        – Abshaʿr
                    
                    
                        O: אבשער In the Sabaitic script, see Introduction 2.8.4. 
                            Ds: Šahrām (1)’s slave?
                                    CIS translates דמם as “liberis eorum,”
                                    i.e. his freed slave.
                            F: Dedicatory inscription, Ḥimyar S:
                            CIS 4/2, 543 E: Jew? The inscription is dedicated to
                                    ישראל ואלההמו רב יהד (Israel and its God, Lord of the Jews), see
                                    Introduction 6.1. This means his master (see previous note) was
                                    Jewish, but he need not have been, see Introduction
                                6.5.4.2. P: Arab.
                                Pen. From Yemen, see
                                    Introduction 7.2.
                            D: – The
                                    inscription is not dated. Late antique date assumed, see
                                    Introduction 8.4.3
                    
                    احدب Arabic (ʾḤDB), see Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    25.  – Aḥdab
                    
                        O: אחדבוי The Aramaic וי suffix can also be viewed as the result of
                                    Iranian influence, see Introduction 2.4.1.
                            Ds: Mataniah (5)’s son F: –
                                S: bShab 60b (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 148)
                                E: –
                                    Appears in rabbinic literature, and bears the title רב (Rav),
                                    see Introduction 6.6.1. 
                            P: Babylonia
                                D: 4th C CE Was a
                                    contemporary of Rav Nahman (Nahmani [1]), who died according to
                                        Seder Tannaim ve-Amoraim, in 320 CE,
                                    see Introduction 8.2.3. 
                        
                        O: אחדבוי See above, n. 2.
                            Ds: Ami (8)’s son F: –
                                S: bShab 83b (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 148)
                                E: – See above, n. 3. 
                            P: Babylonia
                                D: 3rd-4th C CE Was a student of Rav Ḥisda (Ḥesediah [1]),
                                    who died in 309 CE, according to ShGa §
                                    168, see Introduction 8.2.1. 
                        
                        O: אחדבוי The names on the incantation bowls are in Jewish
                                    characters, see Introduction 5.2.1. And see above, n.
                                2.
                            Ds: Aḥatabu (2)’s son F: Incantation bowl, Berlin S:
                            Wohlstein, ZA 8 (1893) 328 E: Jew? The
                                    authors of the Aramaic incantation bowls were Jewish, but there
                                    is no reason to suppose that all their clients were, see
                                    Introduction
                            6.7. P: Babylonia
                                D: Pre-7th C CE On the dating of the Aramaic incantation bowls see
                                    Introduction 8.5.
                        
                    
                    اخطب Harding, ICPIANI, 223, records the
                                    root ËṬB as an element in Arabic names. – Akhṭab
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ḥuyayy (1), Yāsir (1) and Juday (1)’s father,
                            Saʿya (1)’s son This last
                                    relationship is according to Ṭabarī, iii, 4, 2452.,
                                priest In Arabic – من
                                    سبط هارون ابن عمران (of the tribe of Aaron, son of Amram).
                                , of the Banū al-Naḍīr In Arabic – من بنى النضير. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.2.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E: – Found in a long list of names which is included in the
                                    chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the the names of the Jewish
                                    adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His sons
                                    were contemporaries of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                    
                    اذينة Harding, ICPIANI, 34, records the
                                    root ʿÅN as an element in Arabic names.– Udhayna
                    
                        O: عذتية For this form see Lecker, JSAI 10
                                    (1987) 37. The interchange of ا and ع is related to the decline
                                    of the laryngeals in some dialects used by Jews, see
                                    Introduction 2.3.1. The other differences are based on the
                                    position of the points on the letters, see Introduction
                                    2.5.3. Ds: Of
                                Najrān, In Arabic – من
                                    اهل نجران (of the people of Najrān), see Ibn Ḥabīb, munammaq, 94. merchant In Arabic – كان يتسّق في
                                    أسواق تهامة (he was vending in the markets of Tihāma), see
                                    Balādhurī, ansāb, I, 73 and Ibn Ḥabīb,
                                        Munammaq, 94.
                            F: – S: Balādhurī, ansāb, I, 72-3 E: – Described in the text as
                                    يهودي (Jew), see Introduction 6.1. For further details see
                                    Lecker, JSAI 10
                                    (1987) 37.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE Was under the protection of Muḥammad’s grandfather ʿAbd
                                    al-Muṭṭalib b. Hāshim, see Introduction 8.3.3
                    
                    ارش Arabic (ʾRŠ), see Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    37. – Arsh
                    
                    
                        O: ארש This is the transliteration of this name into Jewish
                                    characters.
                            Ds: Najal (1)’s son F:
                            Graffito, Madāʾin Ṣāliḥ S: Jaussen and Savignac,
                            643 E: – The inscription is in Jewish characters, see Introduction
                                    6.2
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: – The graffito is not dated.
                                    Late antique date assumed, see Introduction
                            8.4.3.
                    
                    ازار Not recorded in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    but see SQEAN, Treasury, 181 and SQEAN, Dictionary, 68. – Azār
                    
                        O: ازر Ibn Hishām gives this form as well. On the
                                    addition or fall of the ﺍ see Introduction
                            2.3.5.4. Ds: Of the
                            Banū Qaynuqāʿ In Arabic – من
                                    بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction 6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn
                            Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s,
                            352 E: – Found in a long list of names which is included in the
                                    chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish
                                    adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        
                    
                    اسامة Harding, ICPIANI, 45, records the
                                    form ʾSMT.  – Usāma
                    
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ḥabiba (5)’s son,
                            of the Banū Qurayẓa In
                                    Arabic – من يني قريزة. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    اسد Arabic (ʾSD), see Harding ICPIANI,
                                    42. – Asad
                    
                        O: – Ds: Kaʿb (3)’s father,
                            of the Banū Qurayẓa In
                                    Arabic – من يني قريزة. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: –
                            S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            F: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: ʿUbayd (1)’s son, Thaʿlaba (3) and Asad (3)’s uncle? So in Wāqidī, kitāb al-maghāzī, 503. In Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 387, he is not
                                    mentioned as their relative.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 387 E: Muslim convert
                                    In Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 387, he
                                    is mentioned under the title: ومن اسلم من يهود معهم (and those
                                    of the Jews who converted together with them), see Introduction
                                    6.1.3. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: اسيد For the additional ي as an indication of dialect, see
                                    Introduction 2.3.5.2
                            Ds: Saʿya (1)’s son, Thaʿlaba (3)’s brother, Asad
                            (2)’s nephew? For the
                                    edition mentioning the nephew see Wāqidī, kitāb al-maghāzī, 503-4.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 387 E:
                            Muslim convert See above, n.
                                    6.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                7.
                        O: – Ds: Kaʿb (6)’s cousin, rabbi In Arabic – حبر (חבר), see Introduction 3.2.
                            F: – S: Ṭabarī, i, 902 E: –
                                    Described as one of the two sages who persuaded the king of
                                    Yemen to convert to Judaism. In Arabic – وخرجبهما معه الى اليمن
                                    واتّبعهما على دينهما (he departed from Yemen, took them with him
                                    and embraced their religion), see Introduction 6.1.2.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 4th C CE Said to be a contemporary of Tibān (1) Asʿad (1). On his
                                    dates see Introduction 8.3.1.
                        O: – Ds: Rabīʿ
                                (3)’s son,
                            ʿAnāza (1)’s father F: – S: Muṣʿab,
                            nasab, 92 E: Proselyte? On
                                    this family see Introduction 6.1.2.1. 
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 4th C CE Found in a
                                    genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    اسعد Arabic (ʾSʿD), see Harding, ICPIANI, 44. – Asʿad
                    
                        O: – Ds: Tibān (1), Karib
                            (1), Dhū Nuwās (1)’s father?
                                    Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 19, claims
                                    this, but chronology and inscriptional evidence casts doubts on
                                    this, see Hirschberg, EJ2 9,
                                122. King of Ḥimyar He is mentioned under the heading “How Abū Karib Tibān
                                    Asʿad took possession of the kingdom of the Yemen and his
                                    expedition to Yathrib” (استيلاء ابي ﮎﺮﺏ تبان اسعد على ملك اليمن
                                    وغزوه الى يثرب), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 12.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 12 E:
                                Proselyte For his
                                    alleged conversion see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 12–18. For the conversion’s controversy see
                                    Robin, EQ, 561-9.; second name
                                P: Arab. Pen. D: 385-420
                                CE These are the dates
                                    of his reign, see Introduction 8.3.1.
                        
                    
                    اشرف Harding, ICPIANI, 347, records the
                                    root ŠRF as an element in Arabic names. – Ashraf
                    
                    
                        O: الاشرف Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: Kaʿb (1)’s father, of the Banū al-Naḍīr In Arabic – من بنى النضير. On
                                    this tribe see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    اشعاث This name is recorded as الاشعث (with the Arabic definite
                                    article) in Dhahabī, mushtabih fī asmāʾ
                                        al-Rijāl, 14, 29. It means “one having his hair shaggy,
                                    or dishevelled” or “having the hair defiled with dust and matted
                                    or compacted, in consequence of its being seldom anointed,” see
                                    Lane, AEL, 1558 and Introduction
                                1.5. – Ashʿāth
                    
                        O: الاشعاث Appears in the text with the Arabic
                                    definite article ﺍﻞ, see Introduction 2.5.1, and previous
                                    note. Ds:
                            Qays (8)’s son, of Kinda,
                            tribal leader In Arabic –
                                    الكندي ... وكان رائيسهم (The Kindite ... who was their leader),
                                    and see Lecker,
                                    JAOS 115 (1995)
                                    639-44.
                            F: –
                            S: Ibn al-Kalbī, nasab maʿadd, 1:139 E: Muslim convert This person played an important role in the first Islamic
                                    century. His original Jewishness was suggested by Lecker, JAOS 115 (1995), 639-42, who argues that
                                    there are too many sources linking this family to Jewish
                                    forefathers, but see Introduction 5.1.3.3. ;
                                nickname Lecker,
                                    JAOS 115 (1995) 639,
                                    n. 20, assumes that Ashʿāth was just his nickname and Maʿdikarib
                                    his real name.
                            P: Arab. Pen. From Haḍramawt, see Introduction 7.2.
                                
                            D: Pre-632 CE Was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, see Introduction 8.3.2.
                        
                    
                    اشيع Harding, ICPIANI, 364, records the
                                    root ŠYʿ as an element in Arabic names. – Ashyaʿ
                    
                        O: – Ds: Adversary of the
                                prophet, Found in a long
                                    list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من
                                    يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1. of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In Arabic – بنو قينقاع فهولاء (and those
                                    are Banū Qaynuqāʿ). On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n. 2.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    اعصم Harding, ICPIANI, 423, records the
                                    root ʿṢM as an element in Arabic names. – Aʿṣam
                    
                        O: – Ds: Labīd (1)’s father,
                            of the Banū Zurayq In Arabic
                                    – ومن يهود بني زريق (of the Jews of the Banū Zurayq).
                                
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. He came from Yemen and settled in Yathrib/Medina, see
                                    Cook, JSS 45 (2000) 323-45 and
                                    Lecker, Al-Qanṭara
                                    13 (1992) 561-69, and Introduction 7.2.
                            D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        
                    
                    اما Harding, ICPIANI, 73, records the
                                    forms ʾM and ʾMT. – Amā
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ḍubayʿa
                            (1)’s son, Malkiah (8)’s father
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn al-Kalbī, jamharat al-nasab, 69 E: Proselyte? Was of the Banū ʿAmr b. al-ʿAwf, see Introduction
                                    6.1.2.2. It is not clear whether Amā was already Jewish or not.
                                    Most probably he was not Jewish, but one of his descendants
                                    embraced Judaism.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: Pre-Islamic This book relates the
                                    genealogy of the Banū Quraysh. Lecker, JSAIS 10 (1987) 26, assumes that this genealogy is
                                    pre-Islamic, see Introduction 8.3.3. 
                    
                    انس Arabic (ʾNS), see Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    79.– Anas
                    
                        O: ابو انس On the Abū prefix see
                                    Introduction
                            2.5.2. Ds: F: –
                                S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E: – Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.; second name P: Arab. Pen. D:
                            Pre-632 CE Was a
                                    contemporary of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: Unays The Arabic text is not published, but it
                                    has to be أنيس. On the additional ي as an indication of dialect
                                    see Introduction 2.5.3.2.
                            Ds: Ruhm (1)’s father
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn al-Kalbī (Caskel), ǧamharat an-nasab, I, no.
                            15 II E: Jew? Had a Jewish mother and a
                                    Qurayshī father, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.5. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic Appears in a
                                    genealogical list of which no more precise detail can be given,
                                    see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    اوس Arabic (ʾWS), see
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    84. – Aws
                    
                    
                        O: – Ds: Dan (1)’s son, of
                            the Banū Qurayẓa In Arabic –
                                    من بني قريزة. On this tribe see Introduction
                                6.1.1.1.1. poet He is mentioned in kitāb al-aghāni,
                                    which is a collection of poems and the stories of their
                                    composers.
                            F: – S:
                            kitāb al-aghānī 19:94
                                E: – His father is described in the text as
                                    اليهودي (the Jew), see Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-627
                                CE This is the year of
                                    the massacre of the Banū Qurayẓa, see Introduction
                                8.3.4.
                    
                    اوفى Harding ICPIANI, 58, records the
                                    root ʾF as an element in Arabic names. – Awfā
                    
                        O: ابو اوفى On the Abū prefix see
                                    Introduction 2.5.2.
                            Ds: Naʿaman (3)’s father F: – S: Ibn Hishām,
                                Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E: –
                                    Found in a long list of names which is included in the chapter
                                    اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see
                                    Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: ʿUthmān (1)’s
                            father, F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 361
                                E: – His son Naʿaman (3)’s conversion to
                                    Islam is hypocritically described under the title من اسلم من
                                    احبار يهود نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted Islam hypocritically),
                                    see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 361,
                                    and Introduction 6.1.3.2. He himself was thus Jewish.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 5.
                    
                    باطا Harding, ICPIANI, 108, records
                                    the root BṬ as an element in Arabic names. – Bāṭā
                    
                        O: – Ds:
                            Zubayr (1)’s father, Wahb (1)’s son, of the Banū Qurayẓa In Arabic – من يني قريزة.
                                    On this tribe see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E: – Found in a long list of names which is included in the
                                    chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish
                                    adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    بحري Harding, ICPIANI, 95, records the
                                    form BḤRT. – Baḥrīy
                    
                        O: – Ds: ʿUmar (4)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    بديه Arabic
                                (BDYH), see Harding, ICPIANI, 98.
                        – Budia
                    
                    
                        O: בודיא So in the JTS Rab. 218 (EMC 270) Ms to bSuk 27a and 34b. As the various versions of this name
                                    indicate, it did not have a stable form, and it is not clear
                                    which name is intended, see Introduction 5.1.1.2.1.1. On the
                                    additional ו as a vowel see Introduction 2.3.5.1./בר הדיה So in the Munich 95 to bGit45b,
                                    see previous note. This is probably a scribal “correction,” see
                                    Introduction 2.7.2./בוריא So in the
                                    St. Petersburg – RNL Evr. I 187 Ms to
                                    bGit 45b and in the
                                    Oxford Opp. Add. Fol. 23 to
                                    bSuk 27a, and see
                                    above, n. 2. On the interchange of רand ד see Introduction
                                    2.7.1./בר בי רב So in the Vatican 130 Ms to
                                    bGit 45b, and see
                                    above, n. 2. These words mean “one of the rabbinic academy.”
                                    This is obviously a scribal “correction,” see Introduction
                                    2.7.2. /ברי So in the Vatican 140 Ms to
                                    bGit 45b, and see
                                    above, n. 2. This may have been understood by the scribe as an
                                    abbreviation, see vol. 1, Introduction 2.4.1.1, pp.
                                23-4./בריא So in the Munich 95 and
                                    London – BL Harl. 5508 (400) Mss to
                                    bSuk 27a, and see
                                    above, ns. 2 and 4./חד
                                קא So in the
                                    Munich 140 Ms to
                                    bSuk 27a, and see
                                    above, n. 2. This means, in Aramaic, “one who stood” and is
                                    probably a scribal “correction,” see above, n. 3./בודאי So in the Oxford – Bodl. Heb. e. 51 (2677) ms to
                                    bSuk 27a and in the
                                    New York – JTS Rab. 108 (EMC 319) and Oxford – Bodl. Heb. e. 51
                                    (2677) Mss to
                                    bSuk 34b, and see
                                    above, n. 2. On the י suffix see Introduction
                                2.3.3/ביריא So in the Vatican 134 Ms to
                                        bSuk27a, and see above, ns. 2 and 7.
                                    On the additional י as vowel see Introduction
                                2.3.5.2. Ds: –
                                F: –
                                S: bGit 45b (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 316)
                                E: – Appears in rabbinic literature and bears the title רב, see
                                    Introduction 6.6.1.
                            P: Babylonia
                                D: 5th C CE Was a
                                    contemporary of Rav Ashi (2), who died in 427 CE, according to
                                        ShGa § 186, see Introduction
                                    8.2.1.
                        
                    
                    برأن Arabic (BRʾN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 100. – Barʾān
                    
                    
                        O: בראן The Aramaic incantation bowls are composed in Jewish
                                    characters, see Introduction
                            5.2.1. Ds: Mithr-Dūχt
                            (3)’s son F: Incantation bowl, London S: Levene, CMB, M163 E: Christian? On Jews and Christians in the bowls see Introduction
                                    6.7.2.
                            P: Babylonia
                                D: Pre-7th C CE On the dating of the Aramaic incantation bowls see
                                    Introduction 8.5.
                        
                    
                    برهام Arabic (BRHM), see Harding, ICPIANI, 103. – Barhām
                    
                        O: – Ds: Silsila (1)’s
                            father F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                            Muslim convert? Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1. On pp. 361-2 his hypocritical conversion is
                                    described under the title من اسلم من احبار يهود نفاقا (the
                                    rabbis who accepted Islam hypocritically), see Introduction
                                    6.1.3.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    تابوت Not recorded in Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    but see SQEAN, Treasury, 1345.
                                 – Tābūt
                    
                        O: التابوت Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: Zayd (4)’s father, Rifāʿa (2)’s grandfather, of
                            the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In
                                    Arabic – بنو قينقاع فهولاء (and those are Banū Qaynuqāʿ). On
                                    this tribe see Introduction 6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His grandson was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    تبان Arabic (TBN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 128. – Tibān
                    
                        O: – Ds: Karib (1) Asʿad
                            (1), Joseph (36) Dhū Nuwās (1)’s father? Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 19, claims this, but chronology and
                                    inscriptional evidence casts doubts on this, see Hirschberg, EJ2 9, 122. King of
                                Ḥimyar He is mentioned
                                    under the heading “How Abū Karib Tibān Asʿad took possession of
                                    the kingdom of the Yamen and his expedition to Yathrib” (استيلاء
                                    ابي ﮎﺮﺏ تبان اسعد على ملك اليمن وغزوه الى يثرب), see Ibn Hishām,
                                        Leben Muhammed’s, 12.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 12 E:
                                Proselyte For his
                                    alleged conversion see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 12–18. For the conversion controversy see
                                    Robin, EQ, 561-9.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 385-420
                                CE These are the dates
                                    of his reign, see Introduction 8.3.1.
                    
                    توأمان Name recorded neither in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    nor in SQEAN, see Introduction
                                1.5. – Tawʾamān
                    
                        O: التوأمان Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: Ṣurayḥ (1)’s father, Sibṭ (1)’s son,
                                priest In Arabic – ابن
                                    هارون ابن عمران (son of Aaron, son of Amram).
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13 E:
                                – All persons
                                    mentioned in this genealogy are of the tribe of Banū Qurayẓa,
                                    see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic He is
                                    named in the geneaology of the Jewish tribes in Medina Banū
                                    Qurayẓa and Banū al-Naḍīr. It is impossible to date him more
                                    precisely, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    ترن Arabic
                                (TRN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 144. 
                        – Turan
                    
                        O: תוראן So in the Oxford Opp. Add. Fol. 23 Ms. On the א vowel as
                                    indication of another dialect see Introduction 2.3.5.3.1. On the
                                    ו vowel as indication of another dialect see Introduction
                                    2.3.5.1./תורן So in other mss and prints,
                                    see previous
                            note. Ds: His
                                father Described in
                                    the text as אבי תורן. אבי may be similar to the Arabic Abū
                                    prefix, see Introduction
                            2.5.2. F: –
                                S: bShab 122b (Kosowsky,
                                Babylonico, 96) E: – Appears in rabbinic literature
                                    associating with rabbis, see Introduction 6.6.3.
                            P: Babylonia
                                D: 3rd C CE Was a
                                    contemporary of Samuel (1), who died in 253 CE, according to ShGa § 161 CE, see Introduction
                                    8.2.1.
                    
                    تويت The name is recorded in Dhahabī,
                                    mushtabih, 105, and
                                    see Introduction 1.5.  – Tuwayt
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ḥabiba
                            (7) and Ṣaʿba (1)’s
                            son F: – S: Ibn
                            Ḥabīb, munammaq,
                                507 E: – Had a Jewish mother and a Qurayshī
                                    father, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.5. 
                            P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: Pre- 632 CE His mother was a
                                    contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                            8.3.2.
                    
                    ثابت Harding, ICPIANI, 142, records
                                    the form ÕBTM.  – Thābit
                    
                        O: – Ds: Waqsh
                            (1)’s son, Laylā (1)’s husband, ʿUmar (17)’s father, Rifāʿa (4)’s
                            brother F: – S:
                            Ibn Qudāma, istibṣār, 236
                            E: Muslim convert He is described as
                                    belonging to the Banū Zaʿūrāʾ, see Introduction
                                6.1.3.3. P:
                            Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632 CE Was a contemporary of Muḥammad, who died
                                    in this year, see Introduction 8.3.2.
                        O: –
                            Ds: Zayd (13)’s
                            father F: – S: Ibn
                            Shabba, taʾrīkh, III, 1008
                                E: Jew? His son is described as Jew (يهودي) with two sidelocks
                                    (ذوابتان). If the son was Jewish, so was his father of course.
                                    Yet, for doubts on the Jewishness of the son (understanding it
                                    as a derogatory description made by an opponent) see Lecker, JNES 56 (1997) 259-273.
                            P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: d. 615 CE According to Lecker, JNES 56 (1997) 259, he died in the Battle
                                    of Buʿth, which occurred in this year.
                    
                    ثعلبة Arabic
                                (ÕʿLB), see Harding, ICPIANI, 146.
                        – Thaʿlaba
                    
                    
                        O: –
                            Ds: Malkiah (4)’s father, the
                            imam of the Banū Qurayẓa
                                    In Arabic – إمام بني قريظة. See Lecker, Der
                                        Islam 71 (1994) 280; Samʿānī, al-ansāb, 475.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 17 E:
                            Muslim convert Survived
                                    the massacre of the Jewish Banū Qurayẓa, see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.1, probably having converted to Islam, and see Kister,
                                    JSAI 8 (1986) 61-96
                                    and Lecker, Der Islam 71 (1994)
                                    280-2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Fiṭyawn
                            (1)’s son, head of clan In
                                    Arabic – من بني ثعلبة بن الفطيون (from Banū Thaʿlaba b.
                                    al-Fiṭyawn). On this tribe see Bräu, EI2
                                    10, 433 and Introduction
                            6.1.1.1.4. F:
                            – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E: –; family On
                                    the Banū Thaʿlaba b. Fiṭyawn as a Jewish tribal name see Bräu,
                                        EI2 10, 433 and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.4.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-Islamic
                                    The names of the Jewish tribes and clans in Medina go back to a
                                    founding father, but it is not possible to date this person more
                                    precisely, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        
                        O: – Ds: Saʿya (1)’s son,
                            Asad (3)’s brother F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 387 E: Muslim convert Survived the massacre of
                                    the Banū Qurayẓa, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1, and Kister,
                                    JSAI 8 (1986) 61-96.
                                    He is mentioned as among other Jews who became Muslim. In Arabic
                                    – ومن اسلم من اليهود معهم (the Jews who converted with them to
                                    Islam), see Ibn Hishām,
                                    Leben Muhammed’s, 387.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    4.
                        O: – Ds: ʿAdīy (6)’s son,
                            Khalīfa (1)’s father F: – S:
                            Ibn Qudāma, istibṣār,
                            225-227 E: Jew? He is mentionend as
                                    ancestor of a relative from Ribāb (2), whose Jewishness is
                                    suggested by Lecker, see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993)
                                    157-8, but see Introduction 5.1.3.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE This is
                                    a genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    جابر Arabic (JBR), see Harding, ICPIANI, 151.– Jābir
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ḥusayl
                            (1)’s father F: –
                            S: Ibn Qudāma, Istibṣār, 233
                                E: Jew? Lecker, QdSA 11
                                    (1993) 156, states that when his ancester Jirwa (1) came to
                                    Medina, “Jews where at the peak of their power. Perhaps they
                                    made him convert to Judaism.” This, however, remains unproven,
                                    see Introduction
                            5.1.3.3. P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: 6th C CE His grandson was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    جبل Harding, ICPIANI, 152, records
                                    the form JBLT. – Jabal
                    
                        O: – Ds: ʿUmar (6)’s son,
                            Sukayna (1)’s grandson, of the Banū Qurayẓa In Arabic – من يني قريزة. On this tribe
                                    see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Qushayr (1)’s son,
                            of the Banū Qurayẓa See
                                    above, n. 2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    4.
                        O: – Ds: Muʿādh
                            (1)’s father F: – S: Yaʿqūbī,
                                taʾrīkh, II, 80 E:
                                Jew? His son was a
                                    prominent Muslim under Muḥammad. In a late
                                    tafsir he is
                                    described with two others (Ḥudhayfa [1] and ʿAmmār [2]) as
                                    having been asked to convert to Judaism. The other two, in
                                    another tafsir, are said to have been
                                    asked to return to Judaism. Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993)
                                    assumes that this should also be the case for Muʿādh, and thus
                                    certainly for his father, but see Introduction
                                5.1.3.3. P:
                            Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: جبلة On the ﺓ suffix see Introduction 2.3.3.8.
                            Ds: ʿAdīy (7)’s son, Muʿāwiya (1)’s father F: –
                            S: Ibn al-Kalbī, nasab maʿadd, 1:139 E:
                                Jew? Jewishness
                                    suggested by Lecker, JAOS 115 (1995),
                                    639-42, who argues that there are too many sources linking this
                                    family to Jewish forefathers, but see Introduction
                                5.1.3.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. From Haḍramawt, see Introduction 7.2.
                            D: 6th C CE This is
                                    a genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    جحاش Arabic (JḤŠ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 153. – Jaḥḥāsh
                    
                        O: – Ds:
                            ʿUmar (2)’s father F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 351 E: – Found in a long list of
                                    names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    جدي Arabic (JDY), see Harding, ICPIANI, 156. – Judayy
                    
                        O: – Ds: Akhṭab (1)’s son,
                            Yāsir (1) and Ḥuyayy (1)’s brother, of a fortress A fortress (سلج), which belonged to the
                                    Banū Mālik b. Madhūl and was in the court of his family, is
                                    mentioned in Samhūdī; Wafāʾ al-Wafā, 150
                                    and see also Lecker,
                                    JSAI 6 (1985)
                                    34.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    جنا فة جنافي in Arabic means one who “carries himself in a
                                    proud and self conceited manner,” see Lane, AEL, 471, and Introduction 1.5. – Junāfa
                    
                        O: خنافة ٍSo Guillaumes transcribes the name into
                                    English (Khunāfa). Ibn Hishām gives جنافة. The difference is the
                                    dotting in the first letter, see Introduction 2.5.3.
                            Ds: ʿUmar (10)’s father F: –
                                S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 693 E: – His granddaughter is described as of the
                                    Banū Qurayẓa (see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1), whom the Prophet
                                    married. He thus was also Jewish, see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His granddaughter was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    جرول Name recorded neither in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    nor in SQEAN, and see Introduction
                                    1.5. – Jarwal
                    
                        O: – Ds: Malkiah (10)’s son,
                            Hindōē (1)’s father F: – S:
                            Ibn al-Kalbī,
                            jamharat al-nasab, 626 E: Proselyte? This is the genealogy of the Banū ʿAmr b.ʿAwf, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.2. One of the people mentioned in the genealogy
                                    converted to Judaism, but it is not clear who.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE This
                                    book relates the genealogy of the Banū Quraysh. On such
                                    calculation see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    جروة جرو means “the young one” in Arabic, see Lane, AEL, 415, and Introduction
                                1.5. – Jirwa
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ḥārith’s son
                                    This person is not recorded in this volume, because only his
                                    descendents may have converted to Judaism., Rabīʿ
                            (4)’s father, the Yemenite
                                    In Arabic – اليمان, and see also Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993)
                                    155.
                            F: –
                            S: Ibn Qudāma, Istibṣār, 233
                                E: Jew? On his possible Jewishness see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993)
                                    149-162, but see also Introduction 5.1.3.3. His father was
                                    certainly not
                            Jewish. P: Arab.
                                Pen. Came from Yemen
                                    and settled in Yathrib/Medina, see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993), 155,
                                    and Introduction 2.7.
                            D: 5th C CE He is
                                    mentioned in a genealogical list, see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                    
                    جنادة Arabic (JND), see Harding, ICPIANI, 169. – Junāda
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ḥārith (9)’s son,
                            Malkiah (7)’s father F: – S:
                            Muṣʿab, nasab, 92, 389 E: Proselyte? On this family see Introduction 6.1.2.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 5th C CE Found in
                                    a genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    حارث Arabic (ḤRÕ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 182–3. – Ḥārith
                    
                        O: الحارث Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: Suwayd (1)’s father F: –
                                S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 352 E: – Found in a long list of names which is
                                    included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the
                                    Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: الحارث See above, n. 2.
                            Ds: Zayd (2)’s father F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 352 E: – See above, n. 3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 4.
                        O: الحارث See above, n. 2.
                            Ds: Shalum (3)’s father, ʿAbdullah (3)’s
                            grandfather F: – S: Ibn
                            Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E: – See above,
                                    n. 3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His grandson was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: الحارث See above, n. 2.
                            Ds: ʿAwf (2)’s
                            son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352
                                E: Muslim convert? See above, n. 3. On p. 384 his pretended
                                    conversion is described as بعضهم لبعض تعالوا نومن بما انزل علي
                                    محمد واصحابه غدوة ونكفر به عشية حتى نلبس عليهم دينهم لعلهم
                                    يصنعون كما نصنع فيرجعون عن دينهم (… agreed among themselves that
                                    they should effect to believe in what had been sent down to
                                    Muhammad and his companions at one time and deny it at another
                                    so as to confuse them, with the object of getting them to follow
                                    their example and give up their religion), see Introducion
                                    6.1.3.2. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: حارثة On the ﺓ suffix see Introduction 2.3.3.8.
                            Ds: Rāfiʿ (4)’s father F: –
                                S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 352 E: – See above, n. 3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 4.
                        O: – Ds: Khālida (1)’s
                            father S: – F: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 353 E:
                                – His daughter appears
                                    in this story of her nephew’s conversion from Judaism to Islam,
                                    see ibid. This suggests that he must have
                                    been Jewish.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His daughter was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                        
                        O: – Ds: Zuwayy (1)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 363 E:
                                – His son’s pretended
                                    conversion is described under the title من اسلم من يهود نفاقا
                                    (the rabbis who accepted Islam hypocritically), see Ibn Hishām,
                                        Leben Muhammed’s, 361, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.3.2. Obviously he was Jewish.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE See
                                    above, n. 4.
                        O: – Ds: Zaynab (1)’s father
                                S: – F: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 764 E:
                                – After the massacre
                                    of the Banū Qurayẓa (see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.1), his daughter [Zaynab (1)] tried to poison the
                                    Prophet. Obviously they were Jews.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 4.
                        O: – Ds:
                            Saʿd (4)’s son, Junāda (1)’s father F: –
                                S: Muṣʿab,
                            nasab, 92, 389 E: Proselyte? On this family see Introduction 6.1.2.1.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 5th C CE Found in a genealogical list, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Ḥabiba (9)’s son,
                            Ribāb (1)’s father F: – S:
                            Musʿab, nasab, 200 E:
                                Proselyte? His wife,
                                    Ribāb (1)’s mother, is described as شريفة يهودية (of noble
                                    Jewish extraction), see Introduction 6.1. She married
                                    (successively) four men of the Qurayshī tribe, see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.5. 
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE See
                                    above, n. 4.
                    
                    حطب Arabic
                                (ḤṬB), see Harding, ICPIANI, 192.
                        – Ḥaṭb
                    
                        O: חטיב The names on the incantation bowls are in Jewish
                                    characters, see Introduction 5.2.1. On the י as vowel see
                                    Introduction 2.3.5.2.
                            Ds: – F: Incantation bowl S:
                            CAMIBBM
                            056A E: Jew? The authors of the Aramaic incantation
                                    bowls were Jewish, but there is no reason to suppose that all
                                    their clients were, see Introduction
                            6.7. P: Babylonia
                                D: Pre-7th C CE On the dating of the Aramaic incantation bowls see
                                    Introduction 8.5.
                    
                    حجاج Arabic (ḤJJ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 177. – Ḥajjāj
                    
                        O: الحجّاج Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: ʿUmar (3)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 351 E: – Found in a long list of names which is
                                    included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the
                                    Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    حذيفة Not
                                recorded in Harding. ICPIANI. Lane, AEL, 534, records حدفة as “short,” applied to
                                women, and see Introduction 1.5.  – Ḥudhayfa
                    
                    
                        O: – Ds: Yāmin (3)’s
                                descendent, Probably
                                    not his son but his ancestor, who settled in Medina five
                                    generations before. His real father was called Ḥusayl (1) b.
                                    Jābir (1), see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993)
                                    149-162. Saʿd (5), Safwān (1), Mudlij (1) and Laylā
                            (1)’s brother, Probably
                                    brothers and sisters only on his mother’s side. Ribāb
                            (2) and Ḥusayl (1)’s son F: – S: Masʿūdī, tanbīh, 282 E: Muslim convert His father converted to Islam before the battle of Uḥud,
                                    which took place around 625 CE, see Introduction 6.1.3. Ḥudhayfa
                                    himself is said to have been asked by Jews to return to Judaism
                                    but he did not want to. This description proves that he had once
                                    been a Jew and then converted, see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993)
                                    149-58 and Rāzī, Tafsīr, I,
                                439.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    حربان Arabic (ḤRBN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 182. – Ḥirbān
                    
                        O: ̔Ερβᾶν The Greek transliteration is quite
                                    straightforward, see Introduction 2.22. On the transliteration
                                    of ح (a guttural) with a vowel see vol. 1, Introduction 2.1.2.8,
                                    p. 19.
                            Ds: Religious adversary Described in the text as ἡγούμενον
                                    τοῦ λόγου α̓τῶν, (their spokesman, i.e. the spokesman of the
                                    Jews with whom the archbishop of Tephrensis had a polemic
                                    dispute).
                            F: – S: Gregentius,
                            PG 86, 621 E: Christian convert Described in the title of the treatise
                                    as “Herbano Judaeo” (Herbano the Jew), see Introduction 6.1. At
                                    the end of the composition he is convinced by the “truth” of
                                    Christianity and is baptized, see Introduction 6.1.4.
                            P: Arab. Pen. From Yemen. His opponent is described as
                                    the archiepiscopus of Tephrensis (Τεφρων) the capital of Ḥimyar
                                    (Saphar). The dispute took place in Θρελλέτω
                                (Threlleto).
                            D: Pre-552 CE This was the year in which
                                    Gergentius, who disputed with Ḥirbān, died.
                    
                    حريملة The forms ḤRM and ḤRNLH are recorded for Arabs, see
                                    Harding, ICPIANI, 185. –
                            Ḥuraymila
                    
                        O: – Ds: Rāfiʿ (4)’s father,
                            of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In
                                    Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E: – Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    حسيل Arabic (ḤSL), see Harding, ICPIANI, 189. – Ḥusayl
                    
                        O: حسل Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993) 155,
                                    n.16, records for him the form Ḥisl, which probably transcribes
                                    this
                            name. Ds: Jābir
                            (1)’s son, Ḥudhayfa (1), Saʿd (5), Safwān (1), Mudlij (1) and Laylā
                            (1)’s father? It is not
                                    clear whether he was the father of all of them, or if they were
                                    just brothers and sisters on the mother’s side, who was
                                    (successively) married to four different man of the Qurayshi
                                    tribe, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.5. , Ribāb (2)’s
                            husband, the Yemenite In
                                    Arabic – اليمان.
                            F: –
                            S: Ibn Qudāma, Istibṣār, 233
                                E: Jew? Lecker, QdSA 11
                                    (1993) 156, states that, when his ancester Jirwa (1) came to
                                    Medina, “Jews where at the peak of their power. Perhaps they
                                    made him convert to Judaism.” This, however, remains unproven,
                                    see Introduction
                            5.1.3.3. P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        
                    
                    حصين Arabic (ḤSYN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 191.  – Ḥuṣayn
                    
                        O: الحصين Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: ʿAbdullah (3), Shalum (3)’s son, Ḥārith (3)’s
                            grandson, of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                            Muslim convert According
                                    to Ibn Hishām, the Prophet himself gave him the name ʿAbd-Allāh
                                    when he converted to Islam. His name is found in a long list of
                                    names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1. His conversion is described in ibid. 387 as من اسلم من يهود (Jews [who] became
                                    Muslims), see Introduction 6.1.3. Before he converted, he was
                                    rabbi, see p. 352. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Ribāb (1)’s son,
                            Khiyār (2)’s brother F: – S:
                            Ibn Ḥabīb, munammaq, 507 E:
                                Jew? Had a Jewish
                                    mother and a Qurayshī father who was named Sufyān b. Umayya b.
                                    ʿAbd al-Shams b.ʿAbd al-Manāf. This is the most important clan
                                    of the Quraysh, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.5. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic This book
                                    relates the genealogy of the Banū Quraysh. Lecker, JSAIS 10 (1987) 26, assumes that this
                                    genealogy is pre-Islamic, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                            
                    
                    حفظ Arabic (ḤFÚ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 195. – Ḥafiẓ
                    
                    
                        O: חפץ In Judeo-Arabic, see Introduction 2.8.7. In this script,
                                    the Hebrew צ can stand for the Arabic ص or for the ض. For
                                    further details see Blau, Judaeo-Arabic
                                    (1965). See also Introduction 2.3.4.1.
                            Ds: Ṣafīya (2)’s
                            father, the Prophet’s
                                jār? In Judeo-Arabic –
                                    חפץ אבי צפיה גאריה אלנבי. Leveen, JQR 16
                                    (1925–6) 402, notes, that maybe the feminine form should be read
                                    as the masculine جار which is “neighbor” who stands under the
                                    protection of a certain tribe,” in this case under the
                                    protection of the Prophet himself. 
                            F: – S: Leveen, JQR 16 (1925–6)
                            402 E: Muslim convert On this text, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.3.1. This man’s daughter (Muḥammad’s wife) is
                                    known from Muslim sources. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    حقيق Harding, ICPIANI, 195-6, records
                                    the forms ḤQ and ḤQQN.  – Ḥuqayq
                    
                        O: ابو الحقيق Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1. On the Abū prefix see Introduction
                                    2.5.2.
                            Ds: Rāfiʿ (1), Shalum (2) and Rabīʿ (2)’s father
                            and Kināna (1)’s grandfather, There are different genealogies in this composition. One
                                    describes Kināna as his son, another as his grandson and Rabīʿ
                                    (2)’s son, see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351 and 669. Also, in Salām (2)’s pedigree
                                    his father (Rabīʿ) is apparently erased and he is probably
                                    mistakenly described as Salām (2)’s brother and not as his
                                    brother’s son, see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351. of the Banū al-Naḍīr In Arabic – من بنى النضير.
                                    On this tribe see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351, 669 E: – Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.; second name
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His children were contemporaries of
                                    Muḥammad, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    حكم Arabic (ḤKM), see Harding, ICPIANI, 197. – Ḥakam
                    
                        O: الحكم Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction 2.5.2.
                            Ds: Rayḥāna (2)’s first husband F: – S: Ṭabarī, iii, 2432 E: – Of the Banū
                                    Qurayẓa, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE His widow was
                                    married to Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                    8.3.2.
                    
                    حلوان Arabic (ḤLWN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 199. – Ḥulwān
                    
                    
                        O: חלוון So in the Vatican 108 Ms to. This would
                                    be the transliteration of this name in Jewish characters. This
                                    name was obviously not stable and unknown to the scribes, see
                                    Introduction 5.1.1.2.1.1. On the double ו see Introduction
                                    2.3.4.3./חייון So in the Moscow – Guenzberg 1337-1338 and Oxford Opp.
                                    Add. Fol. 23 Mss, and see previous note. The fall of the ל is
                                    probably a scribal error, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.8.2, p.
                                    20./חזאן So in the Munich 95 Ms, see above, n. 2. This form is
                                    strikingly different from the others and inexplicable, except as
                                    a misunderstanding on the part of the scribe.
                            Ds: Huna (13)’s father F: –
                                S:
                            bShab 139b (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 392) E: – Appears in rabbinic literature and bears
                                    the title רבי (Rabbi), see Introduction
                            6.6,1. P:
                                Babylonia Although he
                                    is designated in this text Rabbi (Palestinian title, see
                                    Introduction 6.6.1), he is the father of a Babylonian Rabbi
                                    designated Rav, and appears only in BT in association with
                                    Babylonian rabbis, see Introduction 5.1.1.1.
                            D: 4th-5th C CE His son was a contemporary of Rav Ashi
                                    (2), who died in 427 CE, according to ShGa § 186, see Introduction 8.2.1.
                    
                    حنش Arabic (ḤNŠ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 205. – Ḥansh
                    
                        O: חניש The names on the incantation bowls are in Jewish
                                    characters, see Introduction 5.2.1. For the י as vowel see
                                    Introduction
                            2.3.5.2. Ds: – F: Incantation bowl, Borsippa S:
                            CAMIBBM
                            073A E: Jew? The authors of the Aramaic incantation
                                    bowls were Jewish, but there is no reason to suppose that all
                                    their clients were, see Introduction
                            6.7. P: Babylonia
                                D: Pre-7th C CE On the dating of the Aramaic incantation bowls see
                                    Introduction 8.5.
                    
                    حنيف Arabic (ḤNF), see Harding, ICPIANI, 206. – Ḥunayf
                    
                        O: – Ds: Saʿd (2)’s father,
                            of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In
                                    Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s,
                            351 E: – Found in a long list of names which is
                                    included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the
                                    Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    حوط Name not recorded in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    but see SQEAN, Treasury, 1502. – Ḥawṭ
                    
                        O: – Ds: Samuel (34)’s son
                                F: – S: Cheiko, Diwan de Samou`al, 22 E:
                                – His father is
                                    described as اليهودي (the Jew), see Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE Nöldeke, Beiträge, 64, gives as
                                    date ca. 550.
                    
                    حيي Arabic (ḤYY), see Harding, ICPIANI, 212. – Ḥuyayy
                    
                        O: – Ds: Akhṭab (1)’s son,
                            Yāsir (1) and Judayy (1)’s brother, Ṣafīya (1)’s father, of a court
                                fortress A fortress
                                    (سلج) which belonges to the Banū Mālik b. Madhūl and was found
                                    in the court of his family is mentioned in Samhūdī, wafāʾ al-wafā, 150 and see also Lecker,
                                    JSAI 6 (1985)
                                    34., priest, In Arabic –من سبط هارون ابن عمران (of the tribe of
                                    Aaron, son of Amram).  of the Banū al-Naḍīr In Arabic – من بنى النضير.
                                    On this tribe see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351, 354 :
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    خارجة Arabic (ËRJ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 218. – Khārija
                    
                    
                        O: – Ds: Rāfiʿ (6)’s father,
                            of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In
                                    Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    خالد Arabic (ËLD), see Harding, ICPIANI, 225. – Khālid
                    
                        O: – Ds: Of the Banū
                                Qaynuqāʿ In Arabic –
                                    من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Ṣuql (1)’s son,
                            Ṣaʿba (1)’s father F: – S: Muṣʿab, nasab,
                            211 E: Proselyte? His pedigree is not
                                    completely clear. He seems to be of one of the Banū ʿAmr b.
                                    al-ʿAwf groups, about whose conversion to Judaism see
                                    Introduction 6.1.2. 
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE His
                                    daughter was a contemporary of Muḥammad see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    خزرج Not recorded in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI.
                                    The form خزرجي (khazraji) is recorded in SQEAN, Dictionary, 513. For
                                    Kahzraj as an Arabic Tribe Name see Watt, EI2 4, 1187. – Khazraj
                    
                        O: الخزرج Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction
                            2.5.1. Ds: Ṣurayḥ
                            (1)’s son, Najjām (1) and ʿUmar (1)’s father, priest In Arabic – ابن هارون ابن عمران (son of
                                    Aaron, son of Amram).
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13 E:
                                – All the persons
                                    mentioned in this genealogy are of the tribe of Banū Qurayẓa,
                                    see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic He is
                                    named in the geneaology of the Jewish tribes in Medina Banū
                                    Qurayẓa and Banū al-Naḍīr. It is impossible to date him more
                                    precisely, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: الخزرج ابو See above, n. 2. On the Abū prefix see Introduction
                                    2.5.2.
                            Ds: Kaʿb (8)’s father, Ḥabība (6)’s son,
                                priest In Arabic –من
                                    سبط هارون ابن عمران (of the tribe of Aaron, son of Amram).
                                
                            F: – S: Ṭabarī, iii, 2452 E: –
                                    His family is described by Ṭabarī as من بني اسرائل (of the
                                    children of Israel), see Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: 5th C CE Mentioned in a genealogy, see Introdution
                                8.3.3.
                    
                    خليفة Arabic (ËLF), see Harding, ICPIANI, 227. – Khalīfa
                    
                        O: – Ds: Thaʿlaba (4)’s son,
                            Ḍahhāk (1)’s father F: –
                            S: Ibn Qudāma, istibṣār, 225-227 E:
                                Jew? It is not clear
                                    who of the people mentioned in the genealogy was Jewish and who
                                    was not, see Lecker, QdSA 11 (1993)
                                    157-6, and see also Introduction 5.1.3.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE His son
                                    was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                    
                    خنافة Arabic (ËNF), see Harding, ICPIANI, 230. – Khunāfa
                    
                        O: – Ds: Simon (7)’s son,
                            ʿUmar (11)’s father F: – S:
                            Ṭabarī, iii, 2432 E: – All this family belonged to the Banū
                                    al-Naḍīr, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE Mentioned in a geneaology, see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Of the Banū
                                Qurayẓa In Arabic – من
                                    يني قريزة. On this tribe see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S: Samhūdī,
                                wafāʾ al-wafā II, 153 E:
                                – Described in the
                                    text as اليهودي (the Jew), see Introduction
                            6.1. P: Arab. Pen.
                            D: Pre-632 CE Was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    خيار Arabic (ËYR), see Harding, ICPIANI, 231. – Khiyār
                    
                        O: خير On the fall of the ا see Introduction 2.3.5.4.
                            Ds: Najjām (2)’s son, Levi (7)’s father,
                                priest In Arabic – ابن
                                    هارون ابن عمران (son of Aaron, son of Amram).
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13 E:
                                – All the persons
                                    mentioned in the genealogy are of the tribe of the Banū Qurayẓa,
                                    see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic He is
                                    named in the geneaology of the Jewish tribes in Medina Banū
                                    Qurayẓa and Banū al-Naḍīr. It is impossible to date him more
                                    precisely, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: الخيار Appears in the text with the Arabic
                                    definite article ﺍﻞ, see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: Ribāb (1)’s son, Ḥuṣayn
                            (2)’s brother His mother
                                    Ribāb (1) was married twice to Qurayshī men, see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.5. 
                            F: – S: Ibn Ḥabīb, munammaq, 507 E: Jew? Had a Jewish mother and a
                                    Qurayshī father, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.5. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic This book
                                    relates the genealogy of the Banū Quraysh. Lecker, JSAIS 10 (1987) 26, assumes that this
                                    genealogy is pre-Islamic, see above, n. 8.3.3.
                            
                    
                    دحية Harding, ICPIANI, 235, records
                                    the form DḤT. – Daḥya
                    
                        O: – Ds: Maḥmūd (2)’s
                            father, of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    دهم Arabic (DHM), see Harding, ICPIANI, 245. – Daham
                    
                        O: דהמי In Sabaitic script, see Introduction 2.8.4. On the י as
                                    vowel see Introduction 2.3.5.2.
                            Ds: Freed slave
                                    CIS translates דמם as “liberis eorum,”
                                    i.e. his freed slave. 
                            F: Dedicatory inscription, Ḥimyar S:
                            CIS 4/2, 543 E: Jew? The inscription is
                                    dedicated to ישראל ואלההמו רב יהד (Israel and its God, Lord of
                                    the Jews), see Introduction 6.1. This means his master (see
                                    above, n. 3) was Jewish, but he need not have been.
                            P: Arab. Pen. From Yemen, where the inscription was found.
                            D: –
                                    The inscription is not dated. Late antique date assumed, see
                                    Introduction 8.4.3
                    
                    دوس Arabic (DWS), see Harding, ICPIANI, 245. – Daws
                    
                    
                        O: – Ds: Of Najrān In Arabic – من اهل نجران
                                    (of the people of Najrān).
                            F: – S: Ṭabarī, i, 926 E: Jew? Described in the text as يهودي. This could be Ṭabarī’s
                                    mistake since Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 26, preserves the name Daws for the
                                    Christian and not the Jew in this conflict.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE He is a contemporary of Joseph (36) Dhū Nuwās (1). On
                                    his dates see Introduction 8.3.1.
                    
                    ديّّال Harding, ICPIANI, 245, records
                                    the form DWLN. – Diyyāl
                    
                    
                        O: Abû ’ddiyâl Nöldeke does not give the name in Arabic, but according
                                    to his transcription of the form in the “sprengersche” edition
                                    (Nr. 1175) it has to be ابو الديال. I have not seen this
                                    edition. On the Abū prefix see Introduction 2.5.2.
                            /Abū al-Zanāb
                                    Nöldeke claims, that the “gothaer” extract names him thus, which
                                    would be ابو الزناد though he provides neither an Arabic text
                                    nor a precise reference. I have not seen this work, and see
                                    previous note.
                            Ds: Poet See Nöldeke, Beiträge,
                                77.
                            F: – S: Nöldeke, Beiträge, 77 E: Proselyete In Nöldeke, Beiträge, 79, the author claims, that al-Bakrī
                                    (Albakrî) described Abū al-Diyyāl as belonging to the Banū
                                    Ḥiṣna, who adopted Judaism, see Introduction 6.1.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic This book
                                    is dedicated to pre-Islamic poetry.
                        
                    
                    ذكوان Arabic (ÅKWN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 255. – Dhakwān
                    
                        O: –
                            Ds: ʿUmar (13), Turnā’s Because she came from
                                    Palestine, she is mentioned in vol. 2. son
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Qutayba, kitāb al-maʿārif, 319 E: Jew? Had a Jewish mother and a Qurayshī father, see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.5. Second name
                            P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: Pre-632 CE Was contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, see Introduction 8.3.2.
                    
                    ذو نواس The name means “the curled,” see Lane, AEL, 2867. The name Nuwās is recorded in SQEAN, Dictionary,
                                    1787, and Treasury, 2537.
                        – Dhū Nuwās
                    
                        O: – Ds:
                            Joseph (36), Tibān (1) Asʿad (1)’s son? As in Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s,
                                    20. However, not all scholars agree, see Robin, EQ, 561-9 and Tobi, EJ2 21. King of Ḥimyar Under the title: ملك ذى نواس (the reign
                                    of Dhū Nuwās) we read: فملكوة (and they made him king).
                                
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 19 E: Proselyte? His conversion is described in Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 12-8, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.2. Second name P: Arab. Pen. Of Yemen, see Robin, EQ, 561-9
                                    and Tobi, EJ2 21, and Introduction
                                    7.2.
                            D: d. 525 CE On this date see Introduction
                                8.3.1.
                        
                    
                    ذو هجن Does not appear in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI.
                                    For the direct translation of the name see, Lane, AEL, 3041-2. The word is used in
                                    connection with camels. It could mean “the racey,” or something
                                    of that nature, and see also Introduction 1.5. –
                            Dhū Hajan
                    
                        O: – Ds: Kaʿb (7)’s
                            grandfather, Mātiʿ (1)’s father, of Ḥimyar In Arabic – الحميري. On the Yemenite
                                    kingdom of Ḥimyar see Hirschberg EJ2 9,
                                    122.
                            F: – S: Ṭabarī, iii, 2475 E: –
                                    On this man, his Jewishness and his family see M. Schmitz,
                                    EI 2 4, 316–7.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE His
                                    grandson died in 652 CE, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        
                    
                    ذو يزن Name recorded neither in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    nor in SQEAN, see Introduction
                                1.5. – Dhū Yazan
                    
                    
                        O: ܕܘܝܙܢ In Syriac, see Introduction 2.8.1.
                                
                            Ds: Masrūq (1)’s general In Syriac – ܚܕ ܡܢ ܪܒܵܝ
                                        ܚܝܵܠܘܬܗ (one of his generals).
                            F: – S: Moberg, Himyarites, 25b E: Jew? He is often described in
                                    this text as cooperating in the Jewish persecutions against
                                    Christians, but he is never described as a Jew himself. He is
                                    described as ܨܠܘܒܐ (crucifier – p. 27b). This title was mostly
                                    reserved by Syriac Christians for Jews.
                            P: Arab. Pen. The events described in the book take place in Yemen
                                    (Himyar).
                            D: 517-25 CE He is a contemporary of Joseph (36) Dhū Nuwās (1). On
                                    his dates see Introduction 8.3.1. 
                    
                    راشد Arabic (RŠD), see Harding, ICPIANI, 278. – Rāshid
                    
                        O: – Ds:
                            Kaʿb (2)’s father, of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe
                                    see Introduction 6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E: – Found in a long list of names which is included in the
                                    chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish
                                    adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    رافع Arabic (RFʿ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 284. – Rāfiʿ
                    
                        O: ابو رافع On the Abū prefix see Introduction 2.5.2.
                            Ds: Ḥuqayq (1), Shalum (2)’s son, the blind, In Arabic – الاعور;
                                    probably identical with Rabīʿ (1). killed in
                                Khaybar, Seems to be
                                    identical with Shalum (2), mentioned on p. 391: وسلام بن الربيع
                                    قال ابن اسحاق وهو ابو رافيع الاعور الذي قتله اصحاب رسول الله
                                    صلعم بخيبر (And Salām Ibn Rabīʿ, Ibn Isḥāq says he is Abū Rāfiʿ
                                    the blind, who was killed by the companions of the Prophet in
                                    Khaybar). of the Banū al-Naḍīr In Arabic – من بنى النضير. On this tribe
                                    see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351, 391 E: – Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.; second name P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632 CE Was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Rāfiʿ (3)’s son, of
                            the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In
                                    Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                6.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    7.
                        O: ابو رافع See above, n. 2.
                            Ds: Rāfiʿ (2)’s father, of the
                            Banū Qaynuqāʿ See above,
                                    n. 8.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                6.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Ḥārith (5)’s son,
                            of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ See
                                    above, n. 8.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                6.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    7.
                        O: – Ds: Ḥuraymila (1)’s
                            son, of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ
                                    See above, n. 8.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                6.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    7.
                        O: – Ds: Khārija (1)’s son,
                            of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ See
                                    above, n. 8.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                6.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    7.
                        O: – Ds: Rumayla (1)’s son,
                            of the Banū Qurayẓa In
                                    Arabic – من يني قريزة (of the Banū Qurayẓa). On this tribe see
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                6.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    7.
                        O: – Ds: Wadīʿa (1)’s son
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 362 E:
                            Muslim convert? His
                                    pretended conversion is described under the title من اسلم من
                                    يهود نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted Islam hypocritically), see
                                    Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 361, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.3.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    7.
                    
                    ربيع Arabic (RBYʿ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 268. – Rabīʿ
                    
                        O: الربيع Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: Ḥuqayq (1)’s son, Kināna (1), Rabīʿ (2) and
                            Shalum (2)’s father, In
                                    the Pedigree of Kināna (1) and Shalum (2) this person is
                                    sometimes erased and his father Ḥuqayq (1) is presented as their
                                    father, see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s,
                                    351, 391, 669. of the Banū al-Naḍīr In Arabic – من بنى النضير.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351, 391 E: – Described
                                    in the text as belonging to the Jewish tribe of Banū al-Naḍīr,
                                    see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His sons were contemporaries of Muḥammad, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: الربيع See above, n.
                            2. Ds: Rabīʿ (1)’s
                            son, Ḥuqayq (1)’s grandson, Kināna (1) and Shalum (2)’s brother, of the
                            Banū al-Naḍīr See above,
                                    n. 4.
                            F: –
                            S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351
                                E: – Found in a long list of names which is
                                    included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the
                                    Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                            6.1.1. P: Arab.
                            Pen.D: Pre-632 CE Was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: الربيع See above, n. 2. 
                            Ds: Nizār (1)’s son, Asad (5)’s father F: – S: Muṣʿab,
                            nasab, 92, 389 E: Proselyte? On this family see Introduction 6.1.2.1. 
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 4th C CE Found in
                                    a genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: الربيعة See above, n. 2. On the ﺓ see Introduction
                                2.3.3.8.
                            Ds: Jirwa (1)’s son, ʿUmar (16)’s father F: –
                            S: Ibn Qudāma, istibṣār, 233
                                E: Proselyte? According to Lecker, QdSA 11 (1993) 149-162, but see also
                                    Introduction
                            5.1.3.3. P: Arab.
                                Pen. His father
                                    probably came to Medina from Yemen, see Lecker, QdSA 11 (1993) 149-162 and Introduction
                                    7.2.
                            D: 6th C CE See
                                    above, n. 13.
                    
                    رزام Arabic (RZM), see Harding, ICPIANI, 277. – Rizām
                    
                        O: – Ds:
                            Yāsir (3)’s father F: – S: 1. Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 980; 2. Ṭabarī, ix, 1959 E: – In Ṭabarī,
                                    ix, 1959, his son is described as اليهودي (the Jew), see
                                    Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        
                    
                    رفاعة Arabic (RFʿ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 284. – Rifāʿa
                    
                    
                        O: – Ds: Qays (2)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Zayd (4)’s son, of
                            the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In
                                    Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: 1. Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352; 2. Ṭabarī, ix, 1959 E: –
                                    In Ṭabarī, ix, 1959, he is described as اليهودي (the Jew), see
                                    Introduction
                            6.1. P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: Pre-632 CE See above, n. 3.
                        O: – Ds: Samuel (33)’s son,
                            Barrah (1)’s brother, the Qurayẓī In Arabic – القرظي. 
                            F: – S: 1. Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 692, 2. Ṭabarī, iii, 2452 E: Muslim convert? Described in the text as a member of the
                                    Jewish tribe of the Banū Qurayẓa, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1. He
                                    was spared in the massacre of his tribe, which suggests that he
                                    converted to Islam.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 7th C CE He is said to have lived during the raid on Banū Qurayẓa
                                    in 627, see Introduction 8.3.4. 
                        O: – Ds: Waqsh (1)’s son, Thābit (1)’s brother F: – S: Wāqidī, kitāb al-maghāzī, I,
                            233 E: Jew? Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993) 158,
                                    claims that he is the brother of the Jewish Thābit, but the
                                    Jewishness of the latter is also doubtful, not to mention this
                                    one, and see Introduction
                            5.1.3.3. P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: Pre-632 CE See above, n.
                            3.
                    
                    رميلة Harding, ICPIANI, 287, records
                                    the root RML as an element in Arabic names. –
                            Rumayla
                    
                        O: – Ds:
                            Rāfīʿ (6)’s father F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 352 E: – Found in a long list of
                                    names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    رهم Not recorded in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI.
                                    Rihm is recorded in SQEAN, Treasury,
                                    1667. From the root رهم (RHM) are derived the words رهام (sheep,
                                    goat) and رهمة (drizzling and lasting rain), see Lane, AEL, 1171. – Ruhm
                    
                        O: Abū Ruhm No Arabic publication is
                                    available, but it has to be ابو رهم. On the Abū prefix see
                                    Introduction 2.5.2.
                            Ds: Anas (2)
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn al-Kalbī (Caskel), ǧamharat an-nasab, I, no.
                            15 II E: Jew? According to Lecker, JSAIS 10 (1987) 24, he had a Jewish
                                    mother and a Qurayshī father, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.5.
                                 Second name P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-Islamic Appears in a genealogical list of which no more precise
                                    detail can be given, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    زبير Harding, ICPIANI, 294, records
                                    the forms ZBRT and ZBRN. – Zubayr
                    
                        O: الزبير Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction
                            2.5.2. Ds: Bāṭā
                            (1)’s son, of the Banū Qurayẓa In Arabic – من يني قريزة. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    زريق Arabic
                                (ZRQ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 297.
                        – Zurayq
                    
                        O: זריקא So in the BT. On the א suffix see
                                    Introduction 2.3.3./זריקן So in the PT. On the ן suffix see vol.
                                    1, Introduction 2.4.3.1, p.
                            27. Ds: – F: – S: 1.
                            yBer 7:5, 11c (Kosovsky, Yerushalmi, 232-3); 2.
                            bBer 3b (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 450-2) E: – Appears in rabbinic
                                    literature and bears the title רבי (Rabbi), see Introduction
                                    6.6.1. 
                            P: Babylonia Although designated Rabbi (a Palestinian title, see
                                    Introduction 6.6.1) he was a Babylonian who migrated to
                                    Palestine, see Hyman, Toldoth, 406-7 and
                                    see Introduction 5.1.1.1.
                            D: 3rd C CE Was a
                                    student of Rav Huna (1), who died in 297 CE, according to ShGa § 167, see Introduction
                                8.2.1.
                        O: Ζερέκα On the transliteration of Semitic names
                                    into Greek see Introduction 2.2.2. For the α suffix see above,
                                    n.
                            2. Ds: Megalus
                            (1)’s father F: Epitaph, Caesarea, Schwabe S:
                            CIJ 889 E: – The provenance of the
                                    inscription in Palestine suggests Jewishness, see Introduction
                                    6.4.3.
                            P: Babylonia His son is described in the text as – Βαβυλωναπίου. For
                                    an alternative explanation of this word, as referring to a
                                    cobbler who makes shoes Babylonian style, see M. Schwabe “A
                                    Greek Inscriptions from the Environs of Caesarea,” BIES 2 (1935) 56-7 (Hebrew).
                            D: 4th C CE Date
                                    suggested by the editor, see Introduction
                            8.4.2.3.
                        O: – Ds: –
                            F: – S: Ibn
                            Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E: – Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.  ; family In Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, the Jewish adversaries of Muḥammad
                                    are listed under the names of tribes including the Banū Zurayq.
                                    This is, thus, the name of one of the tribes, see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.6.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic The names
                                    of the Jewish tribes and clans in Medina go back to a founding
                                    father, and it impossible to date this person more precisely,
                                    see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        
                    
                    زوي Harding, ICPIANI, 303, records
                                    the root ZY as an element in Arabic names. – Zuwayy
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ḥārith (7)’s son
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 363 E:
                            Muslim convert? His
                                    pretended conversion is described under the title من اسلم من
                                    احبار يهود نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted Islam hypocritically),
                                    see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 361-3,
                                    and Introduction 6.1.3.2. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    زيد Arabic (ZYD), see Harding, ICPIANI, 304. – Zayd
                    
                        O: – Ds: Laṣīt (1)’s son, of
                            the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In
                                    Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E:
                            Muslim convert? See below,
                                    n. 6. His pretended conversion is described under the title من
                                    اسلم من احبار يهود نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted Islam
                                    hypocritically), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 361 and Introduction 6.1.3.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Ḥārith (2)’s son,
                            of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ See
                                    above, n. 2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    4.
                        O: – Ds: ʿAdīy (5)’s father,
                            of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ See
                                    above, n. 2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                6.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Tābūt (1)’s son,
                            Rifāʿa (2)’s father, of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ See above, n. 2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n. 6.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 10.
                        O: – Ds: Samuel (32)’s
                            father, of the Banū Qurayẓa In Arabic – من يني قريزة. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n. 6.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 10.
                        O: – Ds: Naḥum (7)’s father,
                            of the Banū Qurayẓa See
                                    above, n. 17.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n. 6.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 10.
                        O: – Ds: Wahb (2)’s father,
                            of the Banū Qurayẓa See
                                    above, n. 17.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n. 6.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 10.
                        O: – Ds: ʿAdīy (4)’s father,
                            of the Banū Qurayẓa See
                                    above, n. 17.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                6.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 10.
                        O: – Ds: Kardam (2)’s
                            father, of the Banū Qurayẓa See above, n. 17.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                6.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 10.
                        O: – Ds: ʿUmar (8)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 362 E:
                            Muslim convert? His
                                    conversion is described under the title من اسلم من احبار يهود
                                    نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted Islam hypocritically), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 361, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.3.2. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    4.
                        O: – Ds: Rayḥāna (2)’s
                            father, ʿUmar (11)’s son F: – S: Ṭabarī, iii, 2432 E: – All this family belonged to
                                    the Banū al-Naḍīr, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE Mentioned in a genaology, see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Samʿūn (7)’s
                            father, Khunāfa (1)’s grandfather S: – F: Ṭabarī, iii, 2432 E: – See above, n.
                                31.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 5th C CE Mentioned in a genaology, see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                        O: –
                            Ds: Thābit (1)’s
                            son F: – S: Ibn
                            Shabba,
                            taʾrīkh al-madīna, vol. III,
                            1008 E: Jew? Described as Jew (يهودي) with two sidelocks (ذوابتان).
                                    Yet for doubts on his Jewishness (understanding it as a
                                    derogatory description made by an opponent) see Lecker, JNES 56 (1997) 259-273.
                            P: Arab.
                                Pen. D: 7th C CE According to Lecker, JNES 56
                                    (1997) 259, his father died in the Battle of Buʿth, which
                                    occurred in 615 CE. He himself was active in the preparation of
                                    the official edition of the Quran under the Khalif ʿUthmān ibn
                                    ʿAffān (644-56 CE).
                        
                        O: – Ds: Qays
                            (7)’s son F: – S: Rāzī, tafsīr, I, 439 E: Muslim convert Was asked to return to Judaism, see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993) 149.
                                    This indicates that before his conversion he was Jewish, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                            D: Pre-632 CE See above, n. 4.
                        
                    
                    سبط Harding, ICPIANI, 309, records
                                    the form SBṬT. – Sibṭ
                    
                        O: السبط Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: Elishaʿ (1)’s son, Tawʾamān (1)’s father,
                                priest In Arabic – ابن
                                    هارون ابن عمران (son of Aaron, son of Amram).
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13 E:
                                – All the persons
                                    mentioned in this genealogy are of the tribe of Banū al-Naḍīr,
                                    see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic He is
                                    named in the geneaology of the Jewish tribes in Medina Banū
                                    Qurayẓa and Banū al-Naḍīr. It is impossible to date him more
                                    precisely, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    سبع Arabic (SBʿ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 309. – Sabaʿ
                    
                        O: – Ds: Malkiah (7)’s son,
                            ʿAbdullah (6)’s father F: – S:
                            Musʿab, nasab, 92 E: Proselyte? On this family see Introduction 6.1.2.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 5th C CE Found in
                                    a genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    سعد Arabic (SʿD), see Harding, ICPIANI, 318. – Saʿd
                    
                        O: – Ds: Elishaʿ (1)’s
                            father, Levi (7)’s son, priest In Arabic – ابن هارون ابن عمران (son of Aaron, son of
                                    Amram).
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13 E:
                                – All the persons
                                    described in the genealogy are of the tribe of Banū Qurayẓa, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic He is
                                    named in the geneaology of the Jewish tribes in Medina Banū
                                    Qurayẓa and Banū al-Naḍīr. It is impossible to date him more
                                    precisely, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Hunayf (1)’s son,
                            of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In
                                    Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E:
                            Muslim convert? Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s,
                                    351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1. In Ibid. 361, his pretended conversion is described under
                                    the title من اسلم من احبار يهود نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted
                                    Islam hypocritically), see Introduction 6.1.3.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: ابو سعد On the Abū prefix see Introduction 2.5.2.
                            Ds: Wahb (4)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 654 E: Muslim convert Belonged to the Jewish
                                    tribe of the Banū al-Naḍīr, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                                    Described as one of اسلما على اموالهما (they converted because
                                    of their property), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 654, and Introduction 6.1.3. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    7.
                        O: – Ds: ʿAnaza (1)’s son,
                            Ḥārith (9)’s father F: – S:
                            Musʿab, nasab, 92 E:
                                Proselyte? On this
                                    family see Introduction 6.1.2.1. 
                            P: Khaybar/Arab. Pen.
                                D: 4th C CE Found in
                                    a genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds:
                            Ḥusayl (1) and Ribāb (1)’s son, Safwān (1) Mudlij (1), Ḥudhayfa (1) and
                            Laylā (1)’s brother Maybe
                                    they where brothers and sisters only on the mother’s side, see
                                    Lecker, QdSA 11 (1993) 157, n.
                                25.
                            F: – S: Ibn Saʿd, ṭabaqāt, VIII, 320, VII, 317
                                E: Jew? Lecker, QdSA 11
                                    (1993) 156 states that when his father’s ancestor Jirwa (1) came
                                    to Medina, “Jews where at the peak of their power. Perhaps they
                                    made him convert to Judaism.” This, however, remains unproven,
                                    see Introduction
                            5.1.3.3. P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: Pre-632 CE See above, n.
                            7.
                        O: سعدى On the ى suffix see Introduction 2.3.3.8.
                            Ds: ʿUmar (18)’s father, of the Banū Qurayẓa In Arabic – من يني قريزة.
                                    On this tribe see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S: Wāqidī, kitāb al-maghāzī, 503 E:
                                – His son converted to
                                    Islam and survived the massacre of the Banū Qurayẓa, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.1.1. He was thus Jewish, see Kister,
                                    JSAI 8 (1986)
                                    61-96.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE In this text we are informed that his son survived the
                                    massacre of the Banū Qurayẓa, see Introduction 8.3.4, being a
                                    contemporary of Muḥammad.
                    
                    سعية Harding, ICPIANI, 317, records
                                    the root Sʿ as an element in Arabic names. – Saʿya
                    
                        O: – Ds: Thaʿlaba (3) and
                            Asad (3)’s father F: – S: Ibn
                            Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 387 E: – His son is
                                    described as ومن اسلم من يهود (one of the Jews who converted to
                                    Islam), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s,
                                    387. See also Introduction 6.1.3, but he was probably
                                    Jewish.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His sons were contemporaries of Muḥammad, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Akhṭab (1)’s
                            father, ʿĀmir (2)’s son, priest In Arabic –من سبط هارون ابن عمران (of the tribe of
                                    Aaron, son of Amram). 
                            F: – S: Ṭabarī, iii, 2452 E: –
                                    This family is described by Ṭabarī as من بني اسرايل (of the
                                    children of Israel), see Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE Mentioned in a genealogy, see Introdution
                                8.3.3.
                        
                    
                    سفوان Harding, ICPIANI, 322, records
                                    the root SFN as an element in Arabic names.  –
                            Safwān
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ḥusayl
                            (1) and Ribāb (2)’s son, Saʿd (5), Mudlij (1) and Laylā (1)’s
                                brother Maybe they
                                    where brothers and sisters only on the mother’s side, see
                                    Lecker, QdSA 11
                                    (1993) 157, n. 25.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Saʿd, ṭabaqāt, VIII, 320 E: Jew? Lecker, QdSA 11 (1993) 156,
                                    states that when his father’s ancestor Jirwa (1) came to Medina,
                                    “Jews where at the peak of their power. Perhaps they made him
                                    convert to Judaism.” This however remains unproven, see
                                    Introduction
                            5.1.3.3. P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    سكين Harding, ICPIANI, 323, records
                                    the forms SKN and SKYNT. – Sukayn
                    
                        O: – Ds: Of the Banū
                                Qaynuqāʿ In Arabic –
                                    من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: سكينة On the ة suffix see Introduction 2.3.3.8.
                            Ds: ʿUmar (6)’s father F: –
                                S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 352 E: – See above, n. 3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    سلسلة Is not recorded in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    nor in SQEAN, see Introduction 1.5. سلسل
                                    means “sweet water that descents easily in the throat” or “young
                                    man, light or active in spirit” see Lane, AEL, 1397. – Silsila
                    
                        O: – Ds: Barhām (1)’s son,
                            of the Banu al-Najjār In
                                    Arabic – من بني النجّار. This was a minor Jewish tribe in
                                    Medina, mentioned also in the Constitution of Medina, signed
                                    between Muḥammad and his Jewish allies in 622 CE, see U. Rubin,
                                    “The Constitution of Medina: Some Notes,” Studia Islamica 62 (1985) 5-23, especially p. 6.
                                
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                            Muslim convert? Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1. In Ibid., 361-2, his
                                    pretended conversion is described under the title من اسلم من
                                    احبار يهود نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted Islam hypocritically),
                                    see Introduction 6.1.3.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    سماك Arabic (SMK), see Harding, ICPIANI, 329. – Sammāk
                    
                        O: – Ds: Poet His speech is presented in
                                    verse.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 657 E: – Described
                                    in the text as اليهودي (the Jew), see Introduction
                                6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    سنينة Arabic (SNYN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 333. – Sunayna
                    
                        O: – Ds: Merchant Described in the text as من
                                    تجار يهود (of the Jewish merchants), who were killed in an
                                    expedition of Muḥammad’s troops.
                             F: – S: Ṭabarī, i, 1372 E: – See previous note, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    سهل Arabic (SHL), see Harding, ICPIANI, 334. – Sahl
                    
                        O: – Ds: ʿUmar (9)’s father,
                            Qays (5)’s grandfather F: – S:
                            Leben Muhammed’s, 363 E:
                                – The pretended
                                    conversion of his grandson is described under the title من اسلم
                                    من يهود نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted Islam hypocritically),
                                    see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 361,
                                    and Introduction 6.1.3.2. Thus, he was Jewish.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE This is a genealogical list, see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                        
                    
                    سويد Harding, ICPIANI, 334, records
                                    the root SWD as an element in Arabic names. –
                            Suwayd
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ḥārith
                            (1)’s son, of the
                            Banū Qaynuqāʿ In Arabic –
                                    من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                            Muslim convert? Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1. On p. 398 his pretended conversion is
                                    described under the title من اسلم من احبار يهود نفاقا (the
                                    rabbis who accepted Islam hypocritically), see Introduction
                                    6.1.3.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        
                    
                    سيحان Not recorded in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI.
                                    The form سيحاني is recorded in SQEAN,
                                        Treasury, 1786.  – Sayḥān
                    
                        O: – Ds: Maḥmūd (1)’s
                            father, of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    شاس Name recorded neither in Harding, ICPIANI, nor in SQEAN, see
                                    Introduction 1.5.  – Shaʾs
                    
                        O: – Ds: ʿAdīy (3)’s son, of
                            the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In
                                    Arabic – من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        
                        O: – Ds: Qays (3)’s son, of
                            the Banū Qaynuqāʿ See
                                    above, n. 2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    4.
                    
                    ششعا The form ŠŠʿʾ is recorded for Arabs (Harding, ICPIANI, 348). – Shashʿā
                    
                    
                        O: ששעה Ds: Ḥananel (2)’s
                            son F: – S:
                            yMeg 1:9, 71c (Kosovsky, Yerushalmi, 264) E: – Appears in rabbinic
                                    literature and bears the title רב (Rav), see Introduction 6.6.1.
                                
                            P: Babylonia Although inly mentioned in PT, his father is a renown
                                    Babylonian Rabbi, and also about his title see previous note,
                                    and see Introduction 7.1. 
                            D: 3rd C CE His
                                    father was a contemporary of Rav (Abba [70]), who died in 247
                                    CE, according to ShGa § 160, see
                                    Introduction 8.2.1. 
                        
                        O: Σάσσου On the Greek transliteration of such names see
                                    Introduction 2.2.2. I assume rather than know that this is the
                                    same name.
                            Ds: Isaac (34)’s father, of Arabia In Greek –
                                ̓Αραβένου.
                            F: Epitaph, catacomb 1, CIJ 1098 S:
                            Beth Sheʿarim 2:79 E: –
                                    Buried in the Jewish cemetery in Palestine, see Introduction
                                    6.4.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                            D: Pre-352 CE This is the year in which
                                    Beth Sheʿarim was destroyed, see Introduction
                                8.4.2.1.
                    
                    صريح The form ṢRWḤ is recorded in Harding, ICPIANI, 372. On the interchange of Y and W see
                                    Introduction 2.3.5.2. –
                            Ṣurayḥ
                    
                        O: الصريح Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ,
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: Khazraj (1)’s father, Tawʾamān (1)’s son,
                                priest In Arabic – ابن
                                    هارون ابن عمران (son of Aaron, son of Amram).
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13 E: –
                                 All the persons
                                    mentioned in this genealogy are of the tribe of Banū Qurayẓa,
                                    see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic He is
                                    named in the geneaology of the Jewish tribes in Medina Banū
                                    Qurayẓa and Banū al-Naḍīr. It is impossible to date him more
                                    precisely, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: S'uraiḥ No Arabic is given in the text. This is the
                                    transcription presented. It should probably be read as صريح
                                    (Ṣurayḥ).
                            Ds: ʿAmram (5)’s son, poet Nöldeke, Beiträge, 79, mentions him as a Jewish poet.
                            F: – S: Nöldeke, Beiträge, 79 Nöldeke mentions the Ḥamāsa of
                                    al-Buḥturī, p. 88, as source. I did not see it.
                            E: –
                                    See above, n. 7.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic Nöldeke’s
                                    book is dedicated to pre-Islamic poetry, see Nöldeke, Beiträge, I-II.
                        
                        O: As's'uraiḥ Nöldeke, Beiträge, 64, gives a
                                    transliteration with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ, see
                                    Introduction 2.5.1. He does not give the Arabic original, which
                                    was probably الصريح (a-Ṣurayḥ).
                            Ds: Samuel (34)’s son F: – S:
                            Nöldeke, Beiträge, 64 Nöldeke mentions a certain version of
                                    the Kitāb al-Ahgānī from Gothar as
                                    source. This is probably an unpublished manuscript. I did not
                                    see it.
                            E: –
                                    His father was a Jewish poet, see Introduction
                                6.5.4.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic See above,
                                    n. 10.
                        
                    
                    صقل Name recorded neither in Harding, nor SQEAN, see Introduction 1.5.  – Ṣuql
                    
                        O: صعل So in Ibn al-Kalbī, jamharat
                                        al-nasab, 69. Muṣʿab, nasab,
                                    207, has صقل.
                            Ds: Khālid (2)’s
                            father F: – S: 1. Muṣʿab, nasab, 207; 2. Ibn
                            al-Kalbī, jamharat al-nasab, 69 E:
                            Proselyte? His pedigree is not completely clear. He
                                    seems to be of one of the Banū ʿAmr b. al-ʿAwf groups, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.2, probably of the subdivision of the Ḍubayʿa.
                                    It is not clear whether one of his forefathers converted to
                                    Judaism. For further details see Lecker, JSAI 10 (1987) 26 and Lecker, MJP, 52-5, but see also Introduction
                                5.1.3.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE This is
                                    a genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    صلوبا Harding, ICPIANI, 375, records
                                    the form ṢLYB. On the interchange of Y and W see Introduction
                                    2.3.5.2. – Ṣalūbā
                    
                        O: – Ds:
                            His son, In the text ابن
                                    صلوبة. of the Thaʿlaba (2) b. al-Fiṭyawn (1) In Arabic – من بني ثعلبة بن
                                    الفطيون. On this tribe see Bräu, EI2 10,
                                    433, and Introduction 6.1.1.1.4.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351,
                                379 The person
                                    mentioned in this location is designated as ابو صلوبا (Abū
                                    Ṣalūbā), i.e. Ṣalūbā’s father. Even if the text refers to a
                                    different person, the father, the name belongs to the same one.
                                
                            E: – Found in a long list of names which is included in the
                                    chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish
                                    adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632 CE
                                    Was a contemporary of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.2.
                    
                    صورياء Harding, ICPIANI, 378, records
                                    the form ṢWRT. – Ṣuriyāʾ
                    
                        O: صوري On the ي suffix see Introduction 2.3.3.8.
                            Ds: ʿAbdullah (1)’s father, of the Thaʿlaba (2) b.
                            al-Fiṭyawn (1) In Arabic –
                                    من بني ثعلبة بن الفطيون. On this tribe see Bräu, EI2 10, 433 and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.4.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 4.
                        O: –
                            Ds: Kināna (2)’s father,
                            client of the Banū Ḥāritha
                                    In Arabic – من يهود بني حارثة. 
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352
                                E: – See above, n. 4. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    صيف Not recorded in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI.
                                    The form Ṣayif is recorded in SQEAN,
                                        Treasury, 1894.  – Ṣayf
                    
                        O: ضيف What exactly his name was is not clear, see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352. For this form
                                    (Ḍayif) see SQEAN, Treasury, 1904. The
                                    difference between the two versions is a small dot, see
                                    Introduction 2.5.3.
                            Ds: ʿAbdullah (2)’s father, of the Banū
                                Qaynuqāʿ In Arabic –
                                    من بنى قينقاع. On this tribe see Introduction
                                6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Malkiah (5)’s
                            father, of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ See above, n. 3.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                4.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 5.
                    
                    ضبيعة Harding,
                                    ICPIANI, 380, records the root ḌBʿ as an
                                element in Arabic names. – Ḍubayʿa
                    
                        O: – Ds: Amā (1)’s father
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn al-Kalbī, jamharat al-nasab, 69 E: Proselyte? Was probably a pagan of the B. ʿAmr b.
                                    al-ʿAwf, see Introduction 6.1.2. It is most likely that this one
                                    was not Jewish, but one of his descendants embraced Judaism, see
                                    Lecker, MJP, 34-161. 
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: Pre-Islamic This book relates the
                                    genealogy of the Banū Quraysh. Lecker, JSAIS 10 (1987) 26, assumes that this genealogy is
                                    pre-Islamic, see Introduction 8.3.3. 
                    
                    ضهاك Name recorded neither in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    nor in SQEAN, see Introduction
                                1.5. – Ḍahhāk
                    
                        O: – Ds: Khalīfa (1)’s son
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Qudāma, istibṣār, 225-7 E: Muslim convert? His father was the paternal cousin of Ribāb (2). He himself
                                    was accused of نفاق (hypocracy) and حب يهود (love of the Jews)
                                    see Lecker QdSA 11 (1993) 157, who writes
                                    “he must have been a former Jew himself,” but see also
                                    Introduction 5.1.3.3.
                            P: ِArab. Pen.
                            D: Pre-632 CE Was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    طلي Arabic (TLY), see Harding, ICPIANI, 389. – Talī
                    
                    
                        O: טלי So in the Vilna print. This would be the transliteration of
                                    this Arabic name into Jewish characters./טלה So in the Jerusalem – Yad
                                    Harav Herzog 1 Ms. On the ה suffix, see vol. 1, Introduction
                                    2.4.2.3, p.
                            25. Ds: Imerta
                            (1)’s father, priest His
                                    daughter is described as בת כהן (priest’s daughter).
                            F: – S:
                            bSan 52b (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 162) E: – Appears in rabbinic
                                    literature where rabbis execute his daughter, see Introduction
                                    6.6.3.
                            P: Babylonia
                                D: 3rd-4th C CE Rav Joseph (5), who died in 323 CE,
                                    according to ShGa § 173, comments on the
                                    faulty action associated with his daughter, see Introduction
                                    8.2.1.
                    
                    عامر Arabic (ʿMR), see Harding, ICPIANI, 436. – ʿĀmir
                    
                        O: – Ds: Waḥwaḥ (1)’s father F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 391 E: – Described in the text as belonging to
                                    the Banū Qurayẓa, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Saʿya (3)’s father,
                            ʿUbayd (2)’s son, priest
                                    In Arabic – من سبط هارون ابن عمران (of the tribe of Aaron, son
                                    of Amram). 
                            F: – S: Ṭabarī, iii, 2452 E: –
                                    This family is described by Ṭabarī as من بني اسرايل (of the
                                    children of Israel), see Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE Mentioned in a genealogy, see Introdution
                                8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Qāmī
                            (1)’s son, Hāshim (1)’s brother F: – S: Ibn Ḥabīb, munammaq, 507
                                E: Jew? Had a Jewish mother and a Qurayshī
                                    father, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.5.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic This book
                                    relates the genealogy of the Banū Quraysh. Lecker, JSAIS 10 (1987) 26, assumes that it is
                                    pre-Islamic, see Introduction 8.3.3. 
                    
                    عاصم Arabic (ʿṢM), see Harding, ICPIANI, 423. – ʿĀṣim
                    
                        O:
                            – Ds: Hindōē (1)’s son, Hindōē
                            (2)’s brother, companion of the Prophet, governor of Medina under
                                Muʿāwiya See Lecker,
                                        JNES 56 (1997) 22, n.
                            12. F: – S: Ibn Ḥabīb, munammaq, 507,
                            n. 6 E: Jew? Had a Jewish mother and a Qurayshī
                                    father, see Introduction
                            6.1.1.1.5. P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: Pre-632 CE According to Lecker, JNES 56 (1997) 22, n. 12, he was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, see Introduction 8.3.2.
                    
                    عباس Arabic (ʿBʾS), see Harding, ICPIANI, 396.– ʿAbbās
                    
                        O: – Ds: Mardas
                            (1)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām,
                                Leben Muhammed’s, 659 E:
                                Jew? In a poetic
                                    context he praises the men of the Jewish Banū al-Naḍīr, next to
                                    another poet (Samāk [1]) who is described as a Jew. Thus he may
                                    have been Jewish himself, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 7th C CE Describes the expulsion of the Banū al-Naḍīr which
                                    occurred in 625 CE, see Introduction 8.3.4.
                        
                        O: עבסי In Palmyrene script, see Introduction 2.8.2. On the י
                                    suffix see vol. 1, Introduction 2.4.1, pp. 23-4. ʿBSY is
                                    recorded as a name in Palmyra (Stark, PNPI, 42).
                            Ds: Julius (3) Aurelius (2), Ḥananiah (31)’s son,
                            Martha (6)’s husband, Batshmaya (1)’s father F:
                            Epitaph and burial cave contract, Palmyra S:
                            Ingholt, Berytus 2 (1935) 78-9 E: Jew? The tomb
                                    is pagan, but this part may have been sold to a Jew, as the name
                                    Ḥananiah suggests, but see Introduction 6.5.3.1. Also, the
                                    family is presented in human form on their sarcophagi, see
                                    Introduction
                            6.8. P: Palmyra
                            D: 219 CE The inscription is dated, see
                                    Introduction 8.4.1.
                    
                    عبد الله In Pre-Islamic names the Arabic ʿBD (slave) is recorded,
                                    see Harding, ICPIANI, 397. The الله
                                    (Allah) element is probably already Islamic. –
                            ʿAbdullah
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ṣūriyāʾ (1)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 351, 396 E: – Described in the text as
                                    saying about himself and his companions: انّا احبار يهود
                                    واشرافهم وساداتهم (We are the rabbis [ḥaverim – see Introduction
                                    3.2], nobles and leaders of the Jews), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 396, and Introduction
                                    6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Ṣayf (1)’s son
                            F: –– S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E: Muslim convert? Found in a long list of names which is included in the
                                    chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish
                                    adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1. In Ibid., 384, his pretended conversion is
                                    described as بعضهم لبعض تعالوا نومن بما انزل علي محمد واصحابه
                                    غدوة ونكفر به عشية حتى نلبس عليهم دينهم لعلهم يصنعون كما نصنع
                                    فيرجعون عن دينهم (… agreed among themselves that they should
                                    effect to believe in what had been sent down to Muhammad and his
                                    companions at one time and deny it at another so as to confuse
                                    them, with the object of getting them to follow their example
                                    and give up their religion), see Introduction 6.1.3.2.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above,
                                n.3.
                        O: –
                            Ds: Ḥuṣayn (1), Shalum (3)’s
                            son, Ḥārith (3)’s grandson, rabbi In Arabic – حبر (חבר), see Introduction 3.2.
                            F: –– S:
                            1. Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352; 2. Leveen,
                                JQR 16 (1925-6) 402 E:
                            Muslim convert See above,
                                    n. 4. ; second name The name ʿAbd-Allāh was given to him by the Prophet on
                                    his conversion to Islam, see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 352.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    3.
                        O: – Ds: Saba (1)’s son
                            F: – S:
                            Ṭabarī, i, 2942 E: Muslim convert Described in the text as يهوديا (Jew),
                                    see Introduction 6.1, who converted to Islam, in Arabic – فاسلم,
                                    see Introduction 6.1.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. From Yemen. In Arabic – من
                                    اهل صنعاء (of the people of Ṣanʿāʾ), see Introduction
                                7.2.
                            D: 7th C CE His conversion is dated to
                                    the caliphate of ʿUthmān b. ʿAffān (c. 579-656), in Arabic –
                                    فاسلم زمان عثمان (he converted in the time of ʿUthmān).
                                
                        O: – Ds: Malkiah (4), of the
                                Kinda In Arabic – من
                                    كندة. On this tribe see Introduction 6.1.1.1.7.
                            F: – S: Ibn Saʿd, Ṭabaqāt, V, 79
                            E: Muslim convert Converted to Islam, and
                                    survived the massacre of the Banū Qurayẓa, see Lecker, Der Islam 71 (1994) 280-2 and also
                                    Kister, JSAI 8
                                    (1986) 61-96, and Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.; second
                            name P: Arab. Pen. Came from Haḍramawt and settled in
                                    Yathrib/Medina. The Kinda were of Hadhramī origin, see Beeston
                                    &amp; Shahīd, EI2 5, 118 and Introduction
                                    7.2.
                            D: 6th-7th C CE His sons are described as transmitters of Hadith from
                                    the second caliph, ʿUmar b. al-Khaṭṭāb (r. 634-644) and his
                                    successor (Samʿānī, al-Ansāb, 475).
                                
                        O: – Ds: Subaʿ (1)’s son, Asmāʾ (1)’s father
                            F: – S:
                            Muṣʿab, Nasab, 92 E: Proselyte? On this family see
                                    Introduction 6.1.2.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE Found in
                                    a genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    عبيد Arabic (ʿBD), see Harding, ICPIANI, 397. – ʿUbayd
                    
                        O: – Ds: Asad (2)’s father,
                            of the Banū Qurayẓa In
                                    Arabic – من يني قريزة. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 387 E:
                                – Survived the
                                    massacre of the Banū Qurayẓa, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1, and
                                    Kister, JSAI 8
                                    (1986) 61-96. He is mentioned among other Jews who became
                                    Muslim. In Arabic – ومن اسلم من اليهود معهم (the Jews who
                                    converted with them to Islam), see Ibn Hishām,
                                        Leben Muhammed’s, 387.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, who died in this
                                    year, see Introduction 8.3.2.
                        
                        O: – Ds: ʿĀmir (2)’s father,
                            Kaʿb (8)’s son, priest In
                                    Arabic – من سبط هارون ابن عمران (of the tribe of Aaron, son of
                                    Amram). 
                            F: – S:
                            Ṭabarī, iii, 2452 E: – This family is described by Ṭabarī as من
                                    بني اسرايل (of the children of Israel), see Introduction
                                    6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 5th C CE Mentioned in a genealogy, see Introdution
                                8.3.3.
                        
                    
                    عثمان Arabic (ʿÕMN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 407. – ʿUthmān
                    
                        O: – Ds: Awfā (2)’s son F: –
                            S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 361 E:
                            Muslim convert? His
                                    pretended conversion to Islam is described under the title من
                                    اسلم من احبار يهود نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted Islam
                                    hypocritically), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 361, and Introduction 6.1.3.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    عدي Arabic (ʿDY), see Harding, ICPIANI, 410-1. – ʿAdīy
                    
                        O: עדי So is the name transliterated into Jewish
                                characters. Ds:
                            Of Sura In Aramaic –
                                    סוראה.
                            F: – S:
                            bGit 31b (Kosowsky, Babylonico, –) E: – Cited by a rabbi as an exact reader of a
                                    biblical verse, see Introduction
                            6.6.3. P: Babylonia
                                D: 4th C CE Was a contemporary of Rav
                                    Nahman (Nahmani [1]), who died in 320 CE, according to Seder Tannaim ve-Amoraim, see
                                    Introduction 8.2.3.
                        
                        O: עדי See above, n. 2.
                            Ds: Nomad In Aramaic – טייעא.
                            F: – S:
                            bMen 69b (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 1131) E:
                                Jew? Appears in
                                    rabbinic literature as an example of someone who experienced a
                                    miracle, but he need not have been Jewish, and his description
                                    as nomad suggest he was not.
                             P: Babylonia
                            D: Post-200 CE Appears in amoraic sources,
                                    see Introduction 8.2.6.
                        
                        O: – Ds: Shaʾs (1)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Zayd (8)’s son, of
                            the Banū Qurayẓa In Arabic
                                    – من بني قريظة. 
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                            Muslim convert? See above,
                                    n. 10. In Ibid., 384, his pretended
                                    conversion is described as بعضهم لبعض تعالوا نومن بما انزل علي
                                    محمد واصحابه غدوة ونكفر به عشية حتى نلبس عليهم دينهم لعلهم
                                    يصنعون كما نصنع فيرجعون عن دينهم (… agreed among themselves that
                                    they should effect to believe in what had been sent down to
                                    Muhammad and his companions at one time and deny it at another
                                    so as to confuse them, with the object of getting them to follow
                                    their example and give up their religion), see Introduction
                                    6.1.3.2. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Zayd (3)’s son, of
                            the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In
                                    Arabic – من بني قينقاع.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                    10.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    14.
                        O: – Ds:
                            Kaʿb (10)’s son, Kaʿb (9) and Thaʿlaba (4)’s father F: – S: Ibn Qudāma,
                                Istibṣār,
                            225 E: Jew? It is not clear who of the
                                    people mentioned in this genealogy was Jewish and who not, see
                                    Lecker, QdSA 11
                                    (1993) 157-8, and Introduction 5.1.3.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE This is a genealogical list, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Jabal (4)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn al-Kalbī, nasab maʿadd, 1:139 E:
                                Jew? Jewishness
                                    suggested by Lecker, JAOS 115 (1995),
                                    639-42, who argues that there are too many sources linking this
                                    family to Jewish forefathers, but see Introduction
                                5.1.3.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. From Haḍramawt, see Introduction 7.2.
                            D: 5th C CE See
                                    above, n. 19.
                        O: عاديا So in kitāb al-aghānī, 19:98. For
                                    the ا suffix see Introduction 2.3.3.3. For ا as an additional
                                    vowel see Introduction
                            2.3.5.3.1. Ds: Samuel
                            (34)’s grandfather F: – S:
                            kitāb al-aghānī, 19:98 E:
                                – His grandson is
                                    described in Cheiko, Diwan de Samouʾal,
                                    22 as اليهودي (the Jew), see Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                            D: Ca. 500 CE Nöldeke, Beiträge, 64, gives the date of 550 CE for his
                                    grandson, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    عزير Arabic (ʿZR), see Harding, ICPIANI, 417. – ʿUzayr
                    
                        O: ابو عزير On the ابو prefix see Introduction 2.5.2.
                            Ds: – F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352
                                E: – Found in a long list of names which is included in the
                                    chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish
                                    adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    عزة Harding, ICPIANI, 417, records
                                    the form ʿZT. – ʿAzza
                    
                        O: ابوعزّة On the Abū prefix see Introduction 2.5.2.
                            Ds: ʿUmar (14), poet In Arabic – الشاعر.
                            F: – S: Ibn Ḥabīb, munammaq, 507
                                E: Jew? Had a Jewish mother and a Qurayshī
                                    father. His mother Ribāb (1) was married (successively) to four
                                    man of different Qurayshī clans, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.5.
                                 Second name
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: Pre-Islamic This book relates the
                                    genealogy of the Banū Quraysh. Lecker, JSAIS 10 (1987) 26, assumes that this genealogy is
                                    pre-Islamic, see Introduction 8.3.3. 
                    
                    عزيز Arabic (ʿZZ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 418. –– ʿAzīz
                    
                        O: – Ds: Malkiah (9)’s son,
                            ʿUmar (14)’s father F:
                            –– S: Ibn al-Kalbī, jamharat al-nasab, 626
                                E: Proselyte? He or one of his ancestors
                                    probably converted to Judaism. This is the genealogy of the Banū
                                    ʿAmr b. ʿAwf, see Introduction 6.1.2, and Lecker, JSAI 10 (1987) 17-39.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 5th C CE This book relates the genealogy of the
                                    Banū Quraysh. On such calculation see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                    
                    عسبي Arabic (ʿSBY), see Harding, ICPIANI, 416. – ʿAsbi
                    
                    
                        O: עשבי So in the Vilna print. This would be the transliteration of
                                    this name in Jewish characters. This name was obviously not
                                    stable and unknown to the scribes, see Introduction
                                    5.1.1.2.1.1./עוסמי So in the London – BL Harl. 5508 (400) and Vatican 134
                                    Mss, see previous note. On the interchange of ס and ש see
                                    Introduction 2.3.4.1. On the additional ו as vowel see
                                    Introduction 2.3.5.1.The replacement of ב with מ is possibly a
                                    scribal error, see vol. 3, Introduction 2.8.4, p.
                                20./עיסמא
                                    So in the Munich 95 Ms, see previous note. On the different
                                    suffix see Intoduction 2.3.3. On the interchange of י and ו see
                                    Introduction 2.3.5.2./עיסבי So in the NY – Columbia X 893 T 141,
                                    Oxford Opp. Add. Fol. 23 and Vatican 108 Mss, see above, n. 2.
                                    On the interchange of ס and ש see Introduction 2.3.4.1. On the
                                    additional י as vowel see Introduction
                                2.3.5.2./עוסבי So in the Cambridge – T-S NS 329.705 Ms, see previous note.
                                    On the interchange of י and ו see Introduction
                                2.3.5.2.
                            Ds: Abba (54)’s father F: – S:
                            bMQ 11a (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 1465) E: – Mentioned in rabbinic
                                    literature as being instructed by rabbis, see Introduction
                                    6.6.3. P: Babylonia
                                D: 3rd C CE His son
                                    was a contemporary of Rav Judah (3), who died in 299 CE,
                                    according to ShGa § 168, see Introduction
                                    8.2.1.
                    
                    عطية Arabic (ʿṬY), see Harding, ICPIANI, 425. – ʿAṭiyya
                    
                        O: ʿAṭiyya Lecker only provides the Latin
                                    transliteration. Ds: The Qurayẓī In Arabic
                                        probably – القرظي but see previous note. F:
                            – S: Lecker, Der Islam 71 (1994) 281, n. 7 Lecker
                                        refers to Muṣʿab al-Zubayrī, Usd
                                            al-ghāba, I, p. 245. I have not seen
                                it. E: Muslim convert? He survived the
                                        massacre of the Banū Qurayẓa as a child and thus probably
                                        converted to Islam afterwards. See also Lecker, Der Islam 71 (1994) 281, n. 7, and
                                        Introduction 6.1.3. P: Arab. Pen. D: 7th C
                                CE
                                        The massacre of the Jewish Banū Qurayẓa which he survived is
                                        dated to 627 CE, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1. and Kister,
                                        JSAI 8 (1986)
                                        61-96. 
                        
                    
                    علم Arabic (ʿLM), see Harding, ICPIANI, 432. –ʿAlam
                    
                    
                        O: אלעלם In Jewish characters. On the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: Samuel (47)’s
                            father F: Graffito, Madāʾin
                            ṢāliḥMédāin Ṣāleḥ S: Jaussen
                            and Savignac, 642 E: – The inscription is in Jewish characters,
                                    see Introduction 6.2.; name? Jaussen and Savignac do not read אלעלם
                                    שמואל as a name, but as “dieu est éternelle! (Abī)
                                Samuel”.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: – The graffito is not dated.
                                    Late antique date assumed, see Introduction
                            8.4.3.
                    
                    عمار Harding, ICPIANI, 436, records
                                    the root ʿMR as an element in Arabic names. –
                            ʿAmmār
                    
                        O: ابو عمار On the Abū prefix see Introduction 2.5.2.
                            Ds: – F:
                            – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 391 E: Muslim convert Described in the text as
                                    belonging to the Banū al-Naḍīr, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2. He
                                    is mentioned under the title الذين حزبوا الاحزاب من رسل اللة
                                    (those who sided with the messenger of God), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 391.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds:
                            Yāsir (4)’s son F: –
                                S: Rāzī, tafsīr, I, 439 E: Muslim
                                convert Was asked to
                                    return to Judaism, see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993) 149.
                                    This indicates that before his conversion he was Jewish, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                            D: Pre-632 CE See above, n.
                            4.
                    
                    عمرو Harding, ICPIANI, 436, records
                                    the root ʿMR as an element in Arabic names. –
                            ʿUmar Transliteration according to Guillaume,
                                        Life of Muḥammad, 239, 240.
                                
                    
                        O: – Ds: Khazraj (1)’s son,
                            Najjām (1)’s brother, the “Hanging lip” In Arabic – وهو هدل. For this
                                    translation see Guillaume, Life of
                                        Muhammad, 7., priest In Arabic – ابن هارون ابن عمران (son of
                                    Aaron, son of Amram).
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13 E:
                                – All persons
                                    mentioned in the genealogy are of the tribe of Banū Qurayẓa, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.1.1. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic He is
                                    named in the geneaology of the Jewish tribes in Medina Banū
                                    Qurayẓa and Banū al-Naḍīr. It is impossible to date him more
                                    precisely, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Jaḥḥāsh (1)’s son
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Ḥajjāj (1)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                7.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Baḥrīy (1)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                7.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 10.
                        O: – Ds: Naʿaman (2)’s
                            father F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                7.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 10.
                        O: – Ds: Jabal (1)’s father,
                            Sukayn (2)’s son F: – S: Ibn
                            Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E: – See above,
                                    n. 7.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 10.
                        O: – Ds: Fardam (2)’s
                            father, client of the Banū ʿAmr b. ʿAwf In Arabic – ومن يهود بني عمرو بن عوف (of
                                    the Jews of the Banū ʿAmr b. al-ʿAwf), see Introduction 6.1. On
                                    this tribe see Introduction 6.1.2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n. 7.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 10.
                        O: – Ds: Zayd (10) and Qays
                            (4)’s father, Sahl (1)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 362-3
                                E: – His son’s pretended conversion to Islam is described under
                                    the title من اسلم من احبار يهود نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted
                                    Islam hypocritically), see Introduction 6.1.3.2. Thus, he was
                                    probably Jewish, see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 361. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 10.
                        O: – Ds: Qays (4)’s son, F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 363 E:
                            Muslim convert? A
                                    conversion is described under the title من اسلم من احبار يهود
                                    نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted Islam hypocritically), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 361, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.3.2. Although not listed among the converts,
                                    two pages later he is described as one of them.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    8.
                        
                        O: – Ds: Junāfa (1)’s son,
                            Rayḥāna (1)’s father F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 693 E: – His
                                    daughter [Rayḥāna (1)] is described as of the Banū Qurayẓa, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.1.1. She was married to the
                                Prophet.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His daughter was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Khunāfa (1)’s son,
                            Zayd (12)’s father F: – S:
                            Ṭabarī, iii, 2432 E: – All this family, according to Ṭabarī,
                                    belonged to the Banū al-Naḍīr, see Introduction
                                6.1.1.1.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE Mentioned in a geneaology, see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                        O: עומר In Judeo-Arabic, see Introduction
                            2.8.7. Ds: Jacob
                            (10), Muḥammad’s companion, the martyr In Judeo-Arabic – אצחב מחמד. He is also described as
                                    אלשהיד (martyr). 
                            F: – S:
                            Leveen, JQR 16 (1925-6) 402 E: Muslim convert In Judeo-Arabic – האולו הם אלי' אלדין גאו אליה ואסלמו עלי
                                    ידיה דלא יציב ישראל שי (These were they who came to him and
                                    adopted Islam in his presence in order that no harm might befall
                                    Israel). This is a Jewish apologetic text, see Introduction
                                    6.1.3.1.; second name, fictitious On the names in this list see
                                    Introduction 6.10.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                            D: Pre-632 CE See above, n.
                            8.
                        O: ابو عمرو On the Abū prefix see Introduction 2.5.2.
                            Ds: Dhakwān (1), Turnā’s Because she came from
                                    Palestine, she is mentioned in vol. 2. son
                            F: –– S:
                            Ibn Qutayba, kitāb al-maʿārif, 319 E: Jew? Had a Jewish mother and a Qurayshī father, see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.5.
                            P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: Pre-632 CE See above, n.
                            8.
                        O: – Ds: ʿAzīz
                            (1)’s son, Malkiah (10)’s father F: – S: Ibn al-Kalbī, jamharat
                                an-nasab, 626 E: Proselyte? This is the genealogy of
                                    the Banū ʿAmr b.ʿAwf, see Introduction 6.1.2 and Lecker, JSAI 10 [1987] 17-39). One of the people
                                    mentioned in the genealogy converted to Judaism. It is not clear
                                    whether ʿAmr was Jewish or not.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE This book relates the genealogy of the
                                    Banū Quraysh. On such calculation see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                        
                        O: – Ds:
                            ʿAzza (1), Ribāb (1)’s son, poet In Arabic – الشاعر.
                            F: –
                            S: Ibn Ḥabīb, munammaq, 507
                                E: Jew? Had a Jewish mother and a
                                    Qurayshī father. His mother Ribāb was married (successively) to
                                    four men of different Qurayshī clans, see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.5. Second name
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: Pre-Islamic This book relates the
                                    genealogy of the Banū Quraysh. Lecker, JSAIS 10 (1987) 26, assumes that it is pre-Islamic,
                                    see Introduction 8.3.3. 
                        O:
                            – Ds: Shuʿathāʾ (1)’s father,
                            head of the Jews, of the Banū Māsika In Arabic – رأس اليهود ... من بني ماسكة من يهود. The
                                    Banū Māsika lived in al-Quff, which is in the Sāfila, or lower part of Medina. Also the Banū
                                    Qaynuqāʾ lived in al-Quff. It is not clear whether the Banū
                                    Māsika where a subdivision of the Banū Qaynuyāʾ or if these
                                    where two separate groups, both living in the same town, see
                                    Lecker, JNES 56 (1997) 264.
                            F: – S: Ibn Thābit, Diwān, II, 208
                                E: – See previous note and Introduction
                                    6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: Pre-Islamic He is mentionend in a poem
                                    which describes pre-Islamic Medina. More cannot be said about
                                    him.
                        O: – Ds: Rabīʿ
                            (4)’s son, Jābir (1)’s father F: –
                            S: Ibn Qudāma, istibṣār, 233
                                E: Proselyte? According to Lecker, QdSA 11 (1993) 149-162, but see also
                                    Introduction
                            5.1.3.3. P: Arab.
                                Pen. Probably his
                                    grandfather Jirwa (1) came to Medina from Yemen. see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993)
                                    149-162, and Introduction 7.2.
                            D: 6th C CE He is
                                    mentioned in a genealogical list, see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                        
                        O: – Ds: Thābit
                            (1) and Laylā (1)’s son
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Qudāma, istibṣār, 236
                            E: Muslim convert? Though he probably was not,
                                    both of his parents were former Jews. His father is described as
                                    belonging to the Banū Zaʿūrāʾ, a Jewish clan which was at some
                                    stage incorporated into the ʿAbd al-Ashhāl, see Introduction
                                    6.1.3.3 and Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993) 158.
                                 P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: Pre-632 CE See above, n. 8.7th C CE
                        O: – D: Saʿd (6)’s son, of
                            the Banū Qurayẓa or Banū al-Naḍīr In this tradition a speech is directed at these two
                                    tribes. Then this person is mentionend as وهو رجل من هم (and he
                                    is one of their men). On these tribes see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.1-2.
                            F: – S: Wāqidī, kitāb al-maghāzī, 503 E:
                            Muslim convert? Survived
                                    the massacre of the Banū Qurayẓa, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1. If
                                    he survived the massacre he probably converted, and see Kister,
                                    JSAI 8 (1986) 61-96.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632 C
                                CE In this text we are
                                    informed that he survived the massacre of the Banū Qurayẓa, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.4. He was obviously a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad.
                        O: עמרו In Nabatean script, see Introduction 2.8.3.
                            Ds: Martha (7)’s father, chief of Taima In Aramaic – ריש
                                תימא.
                            F: Epitaph, Madāʾin Ṣāliḥ S:
                            Altheim and Stiehl, 306 E:
                                – Jewishness indicated
                                    by the biblical name Samuel (48) mentioned in the inscription,
                                    see Introduction 6.5.4.1. The editors interpreted the title of
                                    this person (see previous note) as an indication of the Jewish
                                    influence on the entire region.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 356 CE The inscription is
                                    dated.
                    
                    عمير Harding, ICPIANI, 436, records
                                    the root ʿMR as an element in Arabic names. –
                            ʿUmayr
                    
                        O: – Ds: Yāmin (1)’s father,
                            Kaʿb (5)’s son F: – S: Ibn
                            Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 654 E: – Belonged to
                                    the Banū al-Naḍīr, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    عنازة Harding, ICPIANI, 444, records
                                    the form ʿNZT. – ʿAnāza
                    
                        O: – Ds: Asad (5)’s son,
                            Saʿd (4)’s father F: – S:
                            Muṣʿab, nasab, 92 E:
                                Proselyte? On this
                                    family see Introduction 6.1.2.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 4th C CE Found in
                                    a genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    عفران Arabic (ʿFRN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 425. –ʿUfrān
                    
                    
                        O: עופרן So is the name recorded in the Vilna print. This would
                                    be the transliteration of this name into Jewish characters. This
                                    name was obviously not stable and unknown to the scribes, see
                                    Introduction 5.1.1.2.1.1./עפרון So in the Goettingen 3, London – BL
                                    Harl. 5508 (400) and Vatican 134 Mss to
                                    bMeg 10b as well as
                                    in the Goettingen 3, London – BL Harl. 5508 (400), Munich 95 and
                                    114, Oxford Opp. Add. Fol. 23 Mss to
                                    bMeg 15b, see
                                    previous note. This form is recorded in the Bible in Gen 23:10
                                    for the man who sold Abraham a burial cave in Hebron. The use of
                                    this form here is probably a scribal “correction” based on a
                                    search for a familiar name, rather than the original, see
                                    Introduction 2.7.2./אפדון So in the NY – Columbia X 893 T 141 Ms
                                    to bMeg 10b and in
                                    the NY – Columbia X 893 T 141 Ms to
                                    bMeg 15b, see above,
                                    n. 2. On the interchange of א and ע as an indication of the
                                    decline of the laryngeals see Introduction 2.3.1. On the
                                    interchange of ר and ד see Introduction
                                2.7.1./אפרון So in the Oxford Opp. Add. Fol. 23 Ms to
                                    bMeg 10b, see above,
                                    n. 2 and previous note./איפתון So in the Vatican 134 Ms to
                                    bMeg 15b, see above,
                                    n. 2. This variation is strange and
                            unclear. Ds: Abba
                            (52)’s father F: – S:
                            bMeg 10b (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 1465) E: – Appears in rabbinic
                                    literature as expounding Scripture, see Introduction
                                6.6.3.
                            P: Babylonia
                            D: Post-200 CE Appears only in amoraic,
                                    Babylonian sources, see Introduction 8.2.6.
                    
                    عوف Arabic (ʿWF), see Harding, ICPIANI, 449. – ʿAwf
                    
                        O: – Ds: Malkiah (6)’s
                            father F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Ḥārith (4)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 3.
                    
                    عوير Arabic (ʿWR), see Harding, ICPIANI, 448.  – ʿAwīr
                    
                        O: עוירא So is the transliteration of this name into Jewish
                                    characters.
                            Ds: – F:
                            – S:
                            bPes 73a (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 1137-8) E:
                                – Appears in rabbinic
                                    literature and bears the title רב (Rav), see Introduction 6.6.1.
                                
                            P: Babylonia
                                D: 5th C CE Was a
                                    contemporary of Ravina [Abbin (5)], who died ca. 420 CE, see
                                    Hyman, Toldoth, 1091-2, and see
                                    Introduction 8.2.4.
                    
                    غريض Harding, ICPIANI, 454, records
                                    the form ÇRḌN. – Gharīḍ
                    
                        O: – Ds: Samuel (34)’s
                            father F: – S:
                            kitāb al-aghānī 19:98 E:
                                – His son is described
                                    as اليهودي (the Jew) in Cheiko, Diwan de
                                        Samouʾal, 22, see Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE Nöldeke, Beiträge, 64, gives the
                                    date of 550 CE for his son, see Introduction
                            8.3.3.
                    
                    فردم Harding, ICPIANI, 465, records
                                    the form FRD and on p. 559 the form MFRDM. – Fardam
                    
                        O: – Ds: Kaʿb (4)’s son, of
                            the Banū Qurayẓa In Arabic
                                    – من يني قريزة. On this tribe see Introduction
                                6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds:
                            ʿUmar (7)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 352 E: – See above, n. 3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632 CE
                                    See above, n. 4.
                    
                    فطيون Arabic (FṬYN), Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    462.– Fiṭyawn
                    
                        O: الفطيون Appears in the text with the Arabic
                                    definite article ﺍﻞ, see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: Thaʿlaba (2)’s father, head of
                                clan Of the Banū
                                    Thaʿlaba b. al-Fiṭyawn (بنو ثعلبة بن الفطيون), see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.4., of the Banū Isrāʾīl So in Athīr, taʾrīkh 1, 656, in Arabic – ملك عليهم الفطيون اليهودي
                                    وهو من بني إسرائيل (over them reigns al-Fiṭyawn, the Jew, of the
                                    children of Israel).
                            F: – S: 1.
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351; 2.
                            Athīr, taʾrīkh 1, 656
                                E: – Found in a long list of
                                    names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.; family See previous note.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-Islamic
                                    The names of the Jewish tribes and clans in Medina go back to a
                                    founding father, but it is impossible to date this person more
                                    precisely, see Introduction 8.3.3. 
                        
                    
                    قريظة Not recorded in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    see Introduction 1.5. – Qurayẓa
                    
                        O: – Ds: Head of tribe The tribe of the Banū
                                    Qurayẓa (بنو قريظة) is called after him, see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13 E:
                                – For the Jewish tribe
                                    Banū Qurayẓa see Watt, EI2, 5, 436 and Introduction
                                6.1.1.1.1.; family See previous note.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic The names
                                    of the Jewish tribes and clans in Medina go back to a founding
                                    father, but it is impossible to date this person more precisely,
                                    see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    قشير Arabic (QŠR), see Harding, ICPIANI, 482. – Qushayr
                    
                        O: ابو قشير On the Abū prefix see Introduction 2.5.2.
                            Ds: Jabal (2)’s father F: –
                                S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 352 E: – Found in a long list of names which is
                                    included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the
                                    Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    قيس Arabic (QYS), see Harding, ICPIANI, 492. – Qays
                    
                        O: – Ds: Kardam (1)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Rifāʿa (1)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 3.
                        O: – Ds: Shaʾs (2)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 3.
                        O: – Ds: ʿUmar (8)’s son,
                            ʿUmar (9)’s father, Sahl (1)’s grandson F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                Muhammed’s, 362 E: Muslim convert? His pretended conversion is
                                    described under the title من اسلم من يهود نفاقا (the rabbis who
                                    accepted Islam hypocritically) see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 361, and Introduction 6.1.3.2.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Hawdha (1)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 391 E: –
                                 Described in the text
                                    as belonging to the Banū Qurayẓa, see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 3.
                        O: – Ds:
                            Asmāʾ (1)’s son F: – S: Ibn Ḥabīb, munammaq, 506
                                E: Jew? Had a Jewish mother and a
                                    Qurayshī father, see Introduction
                            6.1.1.1.5. P:
                            Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE Found in a genealogical list, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Zayd (14)’s
                            father F: – S: Rāzī, tafsīr, I, 439 E: – His son was
                                    asked to return to Judaism, see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993) 149.
                                    This indicates that before his conversion he was Jewish and so
                                    was his father, see Introduction 6.1.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE See
                                    above, n. 3.
                        
                        O: – Ds:
                            Maʿdīkarib (1)’s son, Ashʿāth (1)’s father F: –
                            S: Ibn al-Kalbī, nasab maʿadd, 1:139 E: Jew? Jewishness suggested by Lecker, JAOS
                                    115 (1995), 639-42, who argues that there are too many sources
                                    linking this family to Jewish forefathers, but see Introduction
                                    5.1.3.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. From Haḍramawt, see Introduction
                                    7.2.
                            D: 6th C CE See above, n. 13.
                    
                    قينوقاع Harding, ICPIANI, 492, records
                                    the root QYN as an element in Arabic names.  –
                            Qaynuqāʿ
                    
                        O: – Ds: Head of tribe Of the Banū Qanynuqā, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.1.3. 
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 372 E:
                                – Mentioned in a list
                                    of tribes in which they are described as Jewish together with
                                    Qurayẓa and al-Naḍīr, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1-2 and see
                                    Wensink, EI2 4, 824, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.3.; family See previous note.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic The names
                                    of the Jewish tribes and clans in Medina go back to a founding
                                    father, but it is impossible to date this person more precisely,
                                    see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    كرب Arabic (KRB), see Harding, ICPIANI, 497. – Karib
                    
                        O: – Ds: Tibān (1) Asʿad
                            (1), Dhū Nuwās (1)’s father? Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 19,
                                    claims this, but chronology and inscriptional evidence casts
                                    doubts on this see Hirschberg, EJ2 9,
                                    122. King of Ḥimyar He is mentioned under the heading “How Abū Karib Tibān
                                    Asʿad took possession of the kingdom of Yemen and his expedition
                                    to Yathrib” (استيلاء ابي ﮎﺮﺏ تبان اسعد على ملك اليمن وغزوه الى
                                    يثرب), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s,
                                    12.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 12 E:
                                Proselyte For his
                                    alleged conversion see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 12–18. For the conversion’s controversy see
                                    Robin, EQ, 561-9.; second name
                                P: Arab. Pen. D: 385-420
                                CE These are the dates
                                    of his reign, see Introduction 8.3.1.
                    
                    كردم Name recorded neither in Harding, ICPIANI , nor in SQEAN, see
                                    Introduction 1.5. – Kardam
                    
                        O: – Ds: Qays (1)’s son, of
                            the Banū al-Naḍīr In
                                    Arabic – من بنى النضير. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.2.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E: – Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Zayd (9)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    4.
                    
                    كعب Arabic (KʿB), see Harding, ICPIANI, 500. – Kaʿb
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ashraf (1)’s son,
                            leader, poet, of the Banū al-Naḍīr In Wāqidī, I, 184, in Arabic – كان شاعرآ. In Ibn Hishām,
                                        Leben Muhammed’s, 352 – من بني
                                    النضير.
                            F: – S: 1. Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351; 2.
                            Wāqidī, kitāb al-maghāzī, I,
                            184 E: – Found in a long list of names which is included in the
                                    chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish
                                    adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Rāshid (1)’s son
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                4.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    5.
                        O: – Ds: Asad (1)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                4.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    5.
                        O: – Ds: Fardam (1)’s son
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                4.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    5.
                        O: – Ds: ʿUmayr (1)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 654 E:
                                – Of the Banū
                                    al-Naḍīr, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE This is a genealogical list, see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                        
                        O: – Ds: Asad (4)’s cousin, rabbi In Arabic – حبر (חבר), see Introduction 3.2.
                            F: – S: Ṭabarī, i, 902 E: –
                                    Described as one of the two sages who persuaded the king of
                                    Yemen to convert to Judaism. In Arabic – وخرجبهما معه الى اليمن
                                    واتّبعهما على دينهما (he departed from Yemen, took them with him
                                    and embraced their religion), see Introduction 8.3.1.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 4th C CE Said to be a contemporary of Tibān (1) Asʿad (1). On his
                                    dates see Introduction 8.3.1.
                        
                        O: – Ds: Al-Aḥbar (the
                                rabbi), In Arabic –
                                    الاحبار (חבר), see Ṭabarī, v, 2514 and Introduction
                                3.2. Abraham (3), For this second name see Leveen, JQR 16 (1925-6) 402. Mātiʿ (1)’s son, Dhū
                            Hajan (1)’s grandson, Isaac (30)’s father? In a-Ṭabarī, iv, 2474, Kaʿb al-Aḥbār
                                    bears the kunya Abū Isḥāq (ابو اسحاق). On
                                    the Abū prefix see Introduction 2.5.2. , Muḥammad’s
                                companion In
                                    Judeo-Arabic – אצחב מחמד. 
                            F: – S: 1. Ṭabarī, i, 2408; 2.
                            Leveen, JQR 16 (1925-6) 402 E: Muslim convert This is the earliest mention of this important man, and in
                                    this text his Jewishness is only hinted at. In 2514 he is
                                    described as وفي تلك السنة من امارة عمر اسلم (who became a
                                    Muslim in the very year of ʿUmars reign), see Introduction
                                    6.1.3. See also Schmitz, EI2, 4,
                                    316-7.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                            D: d. 652-4 CE See Ṭabarī, iii,
                                2475.
                        
                        O: – Ds: ʿUbayd
                            (2)’s father, Khazraj (2)’s son, priest In Arabic –من سبط هارون ابن عمران (of
                                    the tribe of Aaron, son of Amram). 
                            F: – S: Ṭabarī, iii, 2452
                                E: – Described in the text as من بني اسرائل
                                    (of the children of Israel), see Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 5th C CE Mentioned in a genealogy, see Introduction
                                8.3.3.
                        
                        O: – Ds: ʿAdīy (6)’s son,
                            Ribāb (2)’s father F: – S: Ibn
                            Saʿd, ṭabaqāt, VIII, 320, VII, 317
                                E: Jew? It is not clear who of the people,
                                    mentioned in the genealogy was Jewish. His daughter Ribāb (2)
                                    converted to Islam (اسلمت الرباب) as described in Ibn Saʿd, ṭabaqāt, VIII, 320. That she was Jewish
                                    before, as well as her father, is Lecker’s assumption, but see
                                    Introduction
                            5.1.3.3. P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 12.
                        O: – Ds: ʿAdīy (6)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Saʿd, ṭabaqāt, VIII, 320, VII, 317
                                E: Jew? It is uncertain if he was Jewish. For
                                    the assumption of his daughter’s Jewishness see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993)
                                    157-8, but see Introduction
                            5.1.3.3. P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: 6th C CE See above, n. 12.
                    
                    كنانة Arabic (KNN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 505. – Kināna
                    
                        O: – Ds: Rabīʿ (1)’s son,
                            Ḥuqayq (1)’s grandson, Shalum (2) and Rabīʿ (2)’s brother Kināna is also described as
                                    Ḥuqayq (1)’s son and not his grandson, see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 669. For the erasure of
                                    Rabīʿ in the genealogy of his children who are directly linked
                                    with their grandfather al-Ḥuqayq (1) see also under Shalum
                                    (2).
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E: – Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s,
                                    351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Ṣūriyāʾ (2)’s son
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                            Muslim convert? See above,
                                    n. 3. In Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s,
                                    361, his pretended conversion is described under the title من
                                    اسلم من احبار يهود نفاقا (the rabbis who accepted Islam
                                    hypocritically), see Introduction 6.1.3.2. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    4.
                    
                    لبيد Arabic (LBD), see Harding, ICPIANI, 509.  – Labīd
                    
                        O: – Ds: Aʿṣam (1)’s son,
                                magician In Arabic –
                                    وهو الذ أخز رسول الله صلعم عن نصاءه (who bewitched the apostle
                                    of God so that he could not come at his wives), see Guillaume,
                                        Life of Muḥammad, 240, n. 1 and
                                    Lecker, al-Qanṭara 13 (1992)
                                561-69.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E: Muslim convert Found in a long list of names which is included in the
                                    chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish
                                    adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1. Described in
                                    the text as من يهود بني زريق (of the Jews of the Banū Zarīq),
                                    who were members of the Khazraj, see Lecker, MJP, 9. For Khazraj see Watt, EI2 4, 1187 and see Introduction. Apparently he
                                    converted to Islam to avoid the death penalty, see
                                    Cook, JSS 45 (2000)
                                    323 and Introduction 2.1.2.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    لصيت Name recorded neither in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    nor in SQEAN, see Introduction
                                1.5. – Laṣīt
                    
                    
                        O: لصيب So in Ṭabarī, ix, 1699. Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351, records him as Laṣīt but mentions that
                                    he was called also Laṣīb: ومن بني قينقاع زيد بن اللصيت (ويقال
                                    ابن اللصيب فيما قال ابن هشام) (of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ Zayd b.
                                    al-Laṣīt [according to Ibn Hishām he was also called al-Laṣīb])
                                
                            Ds: Zayd (1)’s son, of the Banū Qaynuqāʿ In Arabic – من بنى قينقاع.
                                    On this tribe see Introduction 6.1.1.1.3.
                            F: – S:
                            1. Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351; 2. Ṭabarī,
                            ix, 1699 E: – Found in a long list of names which is included in the
                                    chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish
                                    adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    ماتع Arabic (MTʿ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 526. – Mātiʿ
                    
                        O: – Ds:
                            Kaʿb (7)’s father, Dhū Hajan (1)’s son F: – S: Ṭabarī, iii, 2475 E: – On his son’s Jewisness and
                                    his family see Schmitz, EI2 4, 316-7.
                                
                            P: Arab. Pen. His father is described as الحميري (the Ḥimyarī). On the
                                    Yemenite kingdom of Ḥimyar see Hirschberg, EJ2 9, 122, and see Introduction 8.3.1.
                            D: 7th C CE His son died in 652 CE, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    محمود Harding, ICPIANI, 200, records
                                    the root ḤMD as an element in Arabic names. –
                            Maḥmūd
                    
                        O: – Ds: Sayḥān (1)’ son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E:
                                – Found in a long list
                                    of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Daḥya (1)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    3.
                    
                    مخيريق Name recorded neither in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    nor in SQEAN, see Introduction
                                1.5. – Mukhayrīq
                    
                        O: – Ds: Rabbi About him it is written:
                                    وكان حبرهم اسلم ومخيريق (and Mukhayrīk their rabbi [ḥaver] who
                                    became Muslim.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351 E:
                            Muslim convert See
                                    previous note.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Of the Banū
                            Thaʿlaba (2) b. Al-Fityawn (1) In Arabaic – وكان احد بنى شعلبة بن الفطيون. On this tribe
                                    see Introduction 6.1.1.1.4.
                            F: – S: Ṭabarī, i, 1424 E: –
                                    Described in the text as خير يهود (the best of the Jews), see
                                    Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: d. 625 Died in the Battle of Uḥud,
                                    see Introduction 8.3.4.
                        
                        O: – Ds: – F:
                            – S: Samhūdī, II,
                                152 E: – It is not clear of what extraction
                                    Mukhayrīq was. Sometimes he is described as belonging to Banū
                                    Qaynuqāʿ, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.3, sometimes as belonging to
                                    the Banū al-Naḍīr, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2. In either case he
                                    was Jewish, see Lecker, JSAI 6 (1985)
                                    32-3. P:
                            Arab. Pen. D: Pre-Islamic In the source it is reported that the
                                    territory of this Jew passed to Muḥammad. From this information
                                    it is impossible to know how early he lived.
                    
                    مدلج Name recorded neither in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    nor in SQEAN, see Introduction
                                1.5. – Mudlij
                    
                        O: – Ds: Ḥusayl
                            (1) and Ribāb (2)’s son, Saʿd (5), Safwān (1) and Laylā (1)’s
                                brother Maybe they
                                    were brothers and sisters only on the mother’s side, see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993)
                                    157.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Saʿd, ṭabaqāt, VIII, 320
                                E: Jew? Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993) 156,
                                    states that when his father’s ancestor Jirwa (1) came to Medina,
                                    “Jews where at the peak of their power. Perhaps they made him
                                    convert to Judaism.” This, however, remains unproven, see
                                    Introduction 5.3.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                            D: Pre-632 CE Was a contemporary of
                                    Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    مر Harding, ICPIANI, 540, records
                                    the root MRR as an element in Arabic names. –
                            Murr
                    
                        O: – Ds: Fāṭima (1)’s
                            father, of Tabālah In
                                    Arabic – من اهل تبالة.
                            F: – S: Ṭabarī, i, 1079 E: Jew? His daughter is described as proselyte (متهودة), see
                                    Introduction 6.1.2. She converted to Judaism but there is no
                                    need to assume that he did too, see Introduction
                                6.5.4.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His daughter was a contemporary of Muḥammad’s father,
                                    see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    مرحب Harding, ICPIANI, 539, records
                                    the form MRḤBM. See also ibid., on p. 275
                                    the root RḤB. – Marḥab
                    
                        O: – Ds:
                            – F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 760 E: – Described
                                    in the text as اليهودي (the Jew), see Introduction
                                6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    مسافع Name recorded neither in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    nor in SQEAN, see Introduction
                                1.5. – Musāfiʿ
                    
                        O: – Ds: –
                                F:
                            – S: Ibn Ḥabīb, munammaq, 506
                                E: Jew? Had a Jewish mother and a Qurayshī
                                    father, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.5. 
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE Was
                                    Muḥammad’s grandfather’s half brother, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                                
                    
                    مشكم Arabic (MŠKM), see Harding, ICPIANI, 548. – Mishkam
                    
                        O: – Ds: Shalum (1)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351, 746 E: – Found in a
                                    long list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء
                                    الاعداء من يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    معاذ Arabic (MʿÅ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 553. – Muʿādh
                    
                        O: – Ds:
                            Jabal (3)’s son
                            F: – S:
                            Yaʿqūbī, taʾrīkh, II, 80 E: Muslim convert Was a prominent Muslim under Muḥammad. In a late
                                    tafsir he is
                                    described with two others (Ḥudhayfa [1] and ʿAmmār [2]) as
                                    having been asked to convert to Judaism. The other two, in
                                    another tafsir, are said to have been
                                    asked to return to Judaism. Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993),
                                    assumes that this should also be the case for this one, but see
                                    Introduction 5.1.3.3.
                             P: Arab.
                            Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    معاوية Harding, ICPIANI, 558, records
                                    the form MʿWYT. – Muʿāwiya
                    
                    
                        O: – Ds: Jabal (4)’s son,
                            Maʿādīkarib (1)’s father F: –
                            S: Ibn al-Kalbī, nasab maʿadd,
                            1:139 E: Jew? Jewishness suggested by
                                    Lecker, JAOS 115 (1995), 639-42, who
                                    argues that there are too many sources linking this family to
                                    Jewish forefathers, but see Introduction 5.1.3.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. From Haḍramawt, see Introduction 7.2.
                            D: 6th C CE This is
                                    a genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    معديكرب Arabic (MʿDKRB), see Harding, ICPIANI, 553. – Maʿdīkarib
                    
                        O: – Ds: Muʿāwiya (1)’s son,
                            Qays (8)’s father, Ashʿāth (1)’s grandfather F: –
                            S: Ibn al-Kalbī, nasab maʿadd, 1:139 E:
                                Jew? Jewishness
                                    suggested by Lecker, JAOS 115 (1995),
                                    639-42, who argues that there are too many sources linking this
                                    family to Jewish forefathers, but see Introduction
                                5.1.3.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. From Haḍramawt, see Introduction 7.2.
                            D: 6th C CE This is
                                    a genealogical list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    منذر Harding, ICPIANI, 585, records
                                    the root NÅR as an element in Arabic names. –
                            Mandhar
                    
                        O: – Ds: Samuel (34)’s son
                                F: – S: 1. Cheiko, Diwan de Samauʾal, 22, 2. kitāb
                                al-aghānī 19:98 E: – His father is described as اليهودي (the
                                    Jew), see Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: ca. 575
                                CE Nöldeke, Beiträge, 64, gives the date of 550 CE
                                    for his father, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    مورق Harding, ICPIANI, 640, records
                                    the root WRQ as an element in Arabic names. –
                            Mawraq
                    
                        O:
                            – Ds: Hirr (1)’s brother F: – S: Ibn Ḥabīb, muḥabbar, 185 E: – Described as اليهودية (the
                                    Jews), see Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic The
                                    sources describe his sister’s clients as of the Jāhiliyya, i.e.
                                    pre-Islamic ‘era of ignorance’.
                    
                    نافع Arabic (NFʿ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 596. – Nāfiʿ
                    
                        O: – Ds: –F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E: – Found in a long list of
                                    names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود
                                    (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a contemporary
                                    of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                        O: ابو نافع On the Abū prefix see Introduction
                            2.5.2. Ds: – F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    3.
                    
                    نجام Arabic (NJM), see Harding, ICPIANI, 582. – Najjām
                    
                        O: –
                            Ds: ʿUmar (1)’s brother,
                            Khazraj (1)’s son, priest In Arabic – ابن هارون ابن عمران (son of Aaron, son of
                                    Amram).
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13 E:
                                – All the persons
                                    mentioned in this genealogy are of the tribe of the Banū
                                    Qurayẓa, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic He is
                                    named in the geneaology of the Jewish tribes in Medina Banū
                                    Qurayẓa and Banū al-Naḍīr. It is impossible to date him more
                                    precisely, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: النجام Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article
                                    ﺍﻞ, see Introduction 2.5.1.
                            Ds: Khiyār (1)’s father, Tanḥum (2)’s son,
                                priest See above, n.
                                    2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                    4.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic See
                                    above, n. 5.
                    
                    نجل Arabic (NJL), see Harding, ICPIANI, 582.  – Najal
                    
                        O: נגל In Jewish characters.
                            Ds: Arsh (1)’s father F:
                            Graffito, Madāʾin Ṣāliḥ F: Jaussen and
                                Savignac, 643 E: – The inscription is in
                                    Jewish characters, see Introduction
                            6.2. P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: – The graffito is not dated. Late
                                    antique date assumed, see Introduction 8.4.3.
                    
                    نزار Not recorded in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    but see SQEAN, 2510. –
                            Nizār
                    
                        O: – Ds: Rabīʿ (3)’s father
                                F: – S: Muṣʿab,
                            nasab, 92, 389 E: Proselyte? On this family see Introduction 6.1.2.1. 
                            P: Arab. Pen
                                D: 3rd C CE Found
                                    in a genealogical list, see Introduction
                            8.3.3.
                    
                    نضير Harding, ICPIANI, 591, records
                                    the forms NḌRT and NḌRN. – Naḍīr
                    
                        O: النضير Appears with the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ in the
                                    text, see Introduction 2.5.1
                            Ds: Head of tribe The Banū al-Naḍīr are called after
                                    him, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 13 E:
                                – On the Jewishness
                                    of the Banū al-Naḍīr see Lecker EJ2 14,
                                    725 and Introduction 6.1.1.1.2.; family See above, n.
                                3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic The
                                    names of the Jewish tribes and clans in Medina go back to a
                                    founding father, but it is impossible to date this person more
                                    precisely, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Ḥabiba (6)’s
                            father, Naḥūm (8)’s son, priest In Arabic – من سبط هارون ابن عمران (of the tribe of
                                    Aaron, son of Amram). 
                            F: – S:
                            Ṭabarī, iii, 2452 E: – This family is described by Ṭabarī as
                                    من بني اسرائل (of the children of Israel), see Introduction
                                    6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 4th C CE Mentioned in a genealogy, see Introdution
                                8.3.3.
                    
                    نفر Arabic (NFR), see Harding, ICPIANI, 596. – Nafar
                    
                        O: נפרי In Palmyrene script, see Introduction 2.8.2. For the י
                                    suffix see
                            Introduction2.2.3.3. Ds: Simon
                            (51)’s father F: Dedication inscription S: Starcky, Semitica 3
                            (1950) 47 E: Jew? Jewishness suggested
                                    based on son’s name, but see Introduction 6.5.3.1. Also on the
                                    slab of the inscription are a bas relief of two deities, see
                                    Introduction 6.8.1.
                            P: Palmyra D: 2nd C CE Date suggested by the editor, see Introduction
                                    8.4.2.3.
                    
                    نفي Arabic (NFY), see Harding, ICPIANI, 597.  – Nafī
                    
                        O: אלנפיו In Jewish characters. On the Arabic definite article ﺍﻞ
                                    see Introduction 2.5.1. On the יו suffix as Nabatean see vol. 1,
                                    Introduction 2.4.5.1, p.
                            28. Ds: ʿAbdi (1)’s
                            son F: Graffito, Madāʾin Ṣāliḥ S: Jaussen and Savignac, 644 E: – The inscription is in
                                    Jewish characters, see Introduction 6.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: – The graffito is not
                                    dated. Late antique date assumed, see Introduction
                                8.4.3.
                        
                    
                    هاشم Arabic (HŠM), see Harding, ICPIANI, 616. – Hāshim
                    
                        O: – Ds: Qāmī
                            (1)’s son, ʿĀmir (3)’s brother F: – S: Ibn Ḥabīb, munammaq 507
                                E: Jew? Had a Jewish mother and a Qurayshī
                                    father, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.5.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic This
                                    book relates the genealogy of the Banū Quraysh. Lecker, JSAIS 10 (1987) 26, assumes that this
                                    genealogy is pre-Islamic, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                            
                    
                    هدي Arabic (HDY), see Harding, ICPIANI, 611. – Hadī
                    
                        O: הדיא So in the Munich 95 and Vatican 140 Mss. On the א
                                    suffix see Introduction 2.3.3. /הידיא So in the Vilna print, see previous note. On the additional
                                    י see Introduction
                            2.3.5.2. Ds: Aḥi
                            (22)’s father F: – S:
                            bGit 35a (Kosowsky, Babylonico, 136) E: – Appears in rabbinic
                                    literature, and is associated with the rabbinic court of law and
                                    the handling of gittin (Jewish divorce documents), see
                                    Introduction 6.6.3.; nickname? On such nicknames see vol. 1,
                                    Introduction 6.1.1, p. 46. Whether the same criteria apply for
                                    the Eastern Diaspora must remain an open question.
                            P: Babylonia D: Pre-427
                                CE Mentioned in a
                                    divorce bill discussed by Rav Ashi (2), who died in this year,
                                    according to ShGa § 186, see Introduction
                                    8.2.1.
                    
                    هوذة Harding, ICPIANI, 612, records
                                    the root HÅT as an element in Arabic names. –
                            Hawdha
                    
                        O: – Ds: Qays (5)’s son, of
                            the Banū Qurayẓa In
                                    Arabic – من يني قريزة. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 391 E:
                            Muslim convert He is
                                    mentioned under the title الذين حزبوا الاحزاب من رسل اللة (those
                                    who sided with the messenger of God), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 391, and Introduction
                                    6.1.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a
                                    contemporary of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.2.
                    
                    وديعة Arabic (WDʿ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 638. – Wadīʿa
                    
                    
                        O: – Ds: Rāfiʿ (8)’s father
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 362
                                E: – His son is described in the text as
                                    one of من اسلم من يهود نفاقاْ (the rabbis who who accepted Islam
                                    hypocritically), see Introduction 6.1.3.2, but he was probably
                                    Jewish.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE His son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    وقش Arabic (WQŠ), see Harding, ICPIANI, 647. – Waqsh
                    
                        O: – Ds: Thābit
                            (1)’s
                            father F: – S:
                            Ibn Qudāma, istibṣār, 236
                                E: – His son converted to Islam. He is
                                    described as belonging to the Banū Zaʿūrāʾ, a Jewish clan which
                                    was at some stage incorporated into the ʿAbd al-Ashhal, see
                                    Introduction 6.1.3.3.
                             P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE This is a genealogical
                                    list, see Introduction 8.3.3.
                    
                    وهب Arabic (WHB), see Harding, ICPIANI, 651. – Wahb
                    
                        O: – Ds: Bāṭā (1)’s father,
                            Zubayr (1)’s grandfather, of the Banū Qurayẓa In Arabic – من يني قريزة. On this
                                    tribe see Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – Found in a long
                                    list of names which is included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من
                                    يهود (the names of the Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction
                                    6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE His
                                    grandson was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                        O: – Ds: Zayd (7)’s son F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352
                                E: – See above, n. 3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a
                                    contemporary of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Judah (17)’s son
                                F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 352 E:
                                – See above, n.
                                    3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    6.
                        O: – Ds: Saʿd (3)’s father,
                            of the Banū al-Naḍīr In
                                    Arabic – من بنى النضير. On this tribe see Introduction
                                    6.1.1.1.2.
                            F: – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 654 E:
                                – His son converted
                                    to Islam as is described in the following text: ولم يسلم من بني
                                    نضير الا رجلان يامن بن عمير بن كعب ابن عم عمرو بن جحاش وابوسعد
                                    بن وهب (nobody of the Banū al-Naḍīr converted besides two men,
                                    Yāmin b. Kaʿb b. ʿUmar b. Jaḥāsh and Abū Saʿd b. Wahab), see
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.1.2. He, however, remained Jewish.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: 6th C CE This is a genealogical list, see Introduction
                                    8.3.3.
                    
                    وحوح Name recorded neither in
                                    Harding, ICPIANI,
                                    nor in SQEAN, see Introduction
                                1.5. – Waḥwaḥ
                    
                        O: – Ds:
                            ʿĀmir (1)’s son, of the Banū Qurayẓa In Arabic – من يني قريزة. On this tribe see
                                    Introduction 6.1.1.1.1.
                            F: – S:
                            Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 391 E: Muslim convert He is mentioned under the title الذين
                                    حزبوا الاحزاب من رسل اللة (those who sided with the messenger of
                                    God), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s,
                                    391, and Introduction 6.1.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632 CE
                                    Was a contemporary of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.2.
                    
                    ياسر Arabic (YSR), see Harding, ICPIANI, 670. – Yāsir
                    
                        O: ابو ياسر On the Abū prefix see Introduction 2.5.2.
                            Ds: Akhṭab (1)’s son, Huyayy (1) and Judayy (1)
                            brother F: – S: Ibn Hishām,
                                Leben Muhammed’s, 351
                                E: – Found in a long list of names which is
                                    included in the chapter اسماء الاعداء من يهود (the names of the
                                    Jewish adversaries), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 351-2, and Introduction 6.1.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a
                                    contemporary of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.2.
                        O: – Ds: Marḥab (1)’s
                            brother F:
                            – S: Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 761 E: – His brother is described in Ibn
                                    Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 760 as اليهودي
                                    (the Jew), see Introduction 6.1.
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    4.
                        O: اليسير Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article
                                    ﺍﻞ, see Introduction 2.5.1. On the additional ي and the fall of
                                    the ا vowels see Introduction 2.5.3.2 and 2.5.3.4.
                            Ds: Rizām (1)’s son, Muḥammad’s opponent He is mentioned in the
                                    chapter غزوة عبد الله بن رواحة لقتل اليسير بن رزام (the
                                    expedition of ʿAbd-Allāh Ibn Riwāʿa to kill al-Jusayr Ibn
                                    Rizām), see Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s,
                                    980. Yāsir lived in Khaybar, an oasis next to Medina, to which
                                    some of the other Jewish tribes were expelled in the Prophet’s
                                    lifetime. According to Ibn Hishām, Yāsir was planning an
                                    expedition against the Prophet to kill him, and that is why he
                                    sent ʿAbd-Allāh Ibn Riwāʿa against Khaybar and especially
                                    against Yāsir.
                            F: – S:
                            1. Ibn Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 980; 2. Ṭabarī,
                            ix, 1959 E: – In Ṭabarī, ix, 1959, he is described as اليهودي (the
                                    Jew), see Introduction 6.1. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE See above, n.
                                    4.
                        O: – Ds: ʿAmmār (2)’s father
                                F: –
                            S: Rāzī, tafsīr, I, 439 E: – His son was asked to return to
                                    Judaism, see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993) 149.
                                    This indicates that before his conversion he was Jewish and so
                                    was his father, see Introduction 6.1.3.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE His
                                    son was a contemporary of Muḥammad, see Introduction
                                8.3.2.
                    
                    يامن Arabic (YMN), see Harding, ICPIANI, 684. – Yāmin
                    
                        O: يامين On the additional ي as vowel see Introduction
                                    2.3.5.2. Ds:
                            ʿUmayr (1)’s son F: – S: Ibn
                            Hishām, Leben Muhammed’s, 654 E: Muslim convert Described as belonging to the Jewish tribe of Banū
                                    al-Naḍīr, see Introduction 6.1.1.1.2. He is described as one of
                                    those اسلما على اموالهما (they converted because of their
                                    property), see Ibn Hishām, Leben
                                        Muhammed’s, 654, and Introduction 6.1.3. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D: Pre-632
                                CE Was a
                                    contemporary of Muḥammad, who died in this year, see
                                    Introduction 8.3.2.
                        O:
                            – Ds: Hirr (1) and Mawraq
                            (1)’s father F: – S: Ibn
                            Ḥabīb, muḥabbar, 185 E:
                                Jew? His daughter is
                                    described as a harlot. There are many harlots mentioned, longing
                                    for the death of the Prophet, but according to Lecker, JAOS 115 (1995) 648, she is the only one
                                    described explicitly as Jewish. 
                            P: Arab. Pen. D:
                                Pre-Islamic The
                                    sources describe his daughter’s clients as of the Jāhiliyya,
                                    i.e. pre-Islamic.
                        O: اليمان Appears in the text with the Arabic definite article
                                    ﺍﻞ, see Introduction 2.5.1. On the interchange of ي and ا vowels
                                    see Introduction 2.5.3.2.
                            Ds: Ḥudhayfa (1)’s ancestor Probably not his father but his
                                    ancestor, five generations before he settled in Medina. His real
                                    father was called Ḥusayl (1) b. Jābir (1).
                            F: – S: Masʿūdī, tanbīh, 282 E:
                                Proselyte? Maybe he
                                    converted to Judaism when he came to Medina, see Lecker,
                                    QdSA 11 (1993)
                                    149-162, but see also Introduction 5.1.3.3.
                                Nickname? His name
                                    means ‘The Yemenite,’ and may refer to his place of origin
                                    rather than to the personal name he was given, see Introduction
                                    7.2.
                            P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 6th C CE This
                                    is a genealogical list, see Introduction
                            8.3.3.
                    
                    يقف Arabic (YQF), see Harding, ICPIANI, 680.  – Yaqaf
                    
                        O: יקף Next to the Jewish charaters, also in
                                    Sabaitic, see Garbini,
                                    Annali 30 (1970) 154
                                    and Introduction 2.8.4.
                            Ds: Judah
                            (19) F: Synagogue
                                inscription, Beit al-Ashwual S: Naveh, OSM, no. 105 E: – The
                                    inscription is in Jewish characters, see Introduction 6.2. It is
                                    a synagogue inscription, see Introduction 6.3. Also, his other
                                    name is biblical, see Introduction 6.5.; second name
                                P: Arab. Pen.
                                D: 4th C CE The
                                    inscription is dated according to the rule of the King
                                    Dharaʾamar Ayman I (ca. 300-310), see Table D: Himyarite rulers
                                    in: K.A. Kitchen, Documentation of Ancient
                                        Arabia, Vol 1 (Liverpool 1994) 16 and Introduction
                                    8.4.1.
                    
                
            
        
    
